Hello and welcome to In Control, the first podcast on control theory.
Here we discuss the science of feedback, decision making, artificial intelligence and much more.
I'm your host Alberto Padoan, live from our recording studio in Lausanne.
Again we're here in the beautiful French speaking side of Switzerland for a nice event which
brought together some of the most brilliant minds out there in control and machine learning.
Today our guest is Anu Anaswamy, Director of the Active and Adaptive Control Laboratory
and Senior Scientist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in the Department
of Mechanical Engineering.
Welcome to the show Anu.
It's my pleasure.
Thanks for having me.
Just before I forget, quick thanks to our sponsors as well to the National Center of
Competence in Research on Dependable Ubiquitous Automation as well as the International Federation
of Automatic Control.
Anu, just to break the ice, what do the first 60 minutes of your day look like?
Ah, well, emails I think.
There's always something very interesting and informative and surprises that sort of
set the day.
And you know, with everybody working around the clock on controls research, colleagues
in Europe have been up for, say for instance, six hours before me and they tell me what's
been going on and that sets the day and, you know, there are then discussions and meetings
and all that.
And so that's basically every 60 minutes of my day start with.
Are you the kind of person that likes, say, to do, I don't know, physical exercise or
meditation or anything like that?
Yeah, I do do them, but later in the day.
But I'd like to start, you know, have my cup of coffee and just jump into work.
And of course, these days, there's always Wordle that starts the day.
Who isn't doing that?
Right.
And then, of course, email.
And that's how my day begins.
Yes.
Yeah.
So maybe, you know, shifting towards the topic of today, which hopefully will be adaptive
control, which is an area of expertise of yours and also its history, I would like to
maybe ask you what has drawn you to control in the first place?
So I know that reading your biography, I saw that you have not just one, but two undergraduate
degrees.
Is that right?
That is correct.
Okay.
And so, yeah, I was curious, given that you have this broad span, what has drawn you to
control?
Okay.
Yeah, no, I'd be very happy to answer that.
So, as you mentioned, I have two undergraduate degrees, and the first one was in math.
And what I found towards the end of that education is that I wanted to really move towards a
more applied aspect of math.
So this was all fine, and I loved doing what I was doing there, but I wanted to know what
it was all for.
So that drew me to my second degree, which was in engineering.
And there was a very specific program where only graduates were admitted.
So it was sort of like a graduate program almost, except that it was more abridged than
the usual undergraduate degree in engineering in India, which is where I come from.
Was five years at that time.
And so this one was more abbreviated in three years, because you've taken all of your courses
already, and that was in electrical engineering.
And so, but even there, what I found was here were all these different courses that mentioned
as to how the universe worked, which was great.
And then was this controls course, which said, no, no, this is basically how you can modify
the universe.
And I thought, wow, that's really cool.
And I got into that more, and the rest is history, I guess.
So I've been working in that same area, I've never left school.
And I still feel that every day I have something to learn.
And then, you know, like I said earlier, what happens in the first 60 minutes, I can't wait
to see what the day brings in terms of new opportunities, new challenges and controls,
research and new solutions.
And yeah.
And but from India, and then you moved to the US to Boston.
So what has brought you on the other side, I would say?
So I applied to graduate school.
And so there were obviously lots of opportunities in the United States.
And it so happened that I met who would become my future advisor, Professor Narendra, who's
also originally from India.
And it so happened, serendipitously, that he was visiting his parents, who happened
to be in the same city that I was from.
And so, you know, I talked to him.
And again, I found even during the, what, 30 minutes of conversation that we might had
that I was learning so much.
And so it was very clear to me that that's where I'd like to go.
And so when Yale University offered me admission, I just took that.
And so, so before Boston, that's New Haven, Connecticut.
And that's where I did my PhD in adaptive control.
Okay.
Yeah.
So this is actually a good assist for me to ask you, what is adaptive control or even
what is adaptation?
So before we delve into this topic, I think I should mention that, well, you wrote one
of the Bibles of adaptive control.
And I do suggest to everyone in the audience to check out the first chapter of the book
Stable Adaptive Systems by Anu and Professor Narendra, because there is a really fantastic
section about how to even define adaptation.
And it seemed absolutely non-obvious when the whole field started.
So maybe you can tell us a bit more about that.
Absolutely.
So adaptation is exactly what the English word means, it's, you know, as it is defined
in biology, advantageous confirmation of an organism to changes in its environment.
So interestingly enough, and I don't know if this was quite your question, but let me
answer if it's a different question, then apologies.
So in adaptation, that concept is the one that caught the imagination of a lot of flight
control engineers and admirals.
And so what they really wanted to do was to design systems, design controllers that figured
on the fly.
And again, the emphasis is on the fly, meaning in real time, as to how to adjust its structure
so that it adapted to changes in the environment and corrected itself and behaved.
So even before theory, adaptive control theory came into being, adaptive control practice
was already there.
So it's one of those interesting cases where practice was ahead of theory.
And so there was this one specific hypersonics program called X-15, where the different control
loops that they had, they chose to make one of them adaptive.
And they actually had several successful flights where the notion of adaptation was basically
in the form of control gains in the feedback loop that basically toggled between two different
values.
And they did that on the basis of what they were measuring.
So in some sense, an exact manifestation of advantageous changes in the organism in response
to changes in the environment.
And they had several successful flights that basically did that.
But then I'm sure we will get more into what happened next.
Absolutely.
That was really the idea behind adaptive control.
And the symposia that were held on adaptive systems at that time tried to capture that
essence in the definition of an adaptive system.
So and then came lots of different efforts in trying to come to a very crisp and useful
definition of adaptation and adaptive control.
And that's what we tried to capture in that introduction.
And one thing left to another.
And then it sort of came to what we know as adaptive control now.
But we can get into that later.
Absolutely.
So I'm glad you mentioned that.
I mean, I guess the main motivation for the development of adaptive control and now we're
talking about pretty much the 60s, I would say, or even before that, of course, we can
trace it back to Norbert Wiener and we can even go probably even backwards.
But I guess the 60s, between the 60s and the 65, is what is called the brave era of adaptive
control. And really, it's fascinating to see how many concepts have been developed just
in that five years span.
So I don't know.
Do you have any thoughts about the developments specifically in that time range?
So, yes.
So I mentioned the symposium, and that was a time when people were talking about and
even implementing adaptive control in flight control.
And around the same time is when the concept of state was being defined.
And, you know, the seminal papers by Kallman, Miranda and Ho came at that time.
And dynamic systems and control systems started to get codified around that around that
time as well.
And so people were beginning to understand how to implement the notions of feedback
control and the methods by Black and Bode and Nyquist and understanding closed loop
control system design using by analyzing forward loop and so on.
So it's interesting to see, you know, that the history of feedback control is almost or
rather the history of adaptive control systems has been as long as at least as long as
the history of control systems, because it's very easy, just like feedback is such a
fundamental and conceptually simple idea to understand and to get motivated by.
So is adaptation.
And so, in fact, you could argue that, you know, as you think about it at a very
philosophical level, the idea of a feedback control system is not that far from the idea
of an adaptive control system.
So I would say those many of those fundamentals started to get defined around that time.
But then I think we probably go towards the early 70s.
If you want, I can get into into that.
Yeah. So I would like to maybe add a few things about this brave era and then we can
definitely move on to the 70s.
So what I personally found fascinating was that there were incredibly influential people
working in this specific time range.
So between the let's say until the 1965, that we're focusing on adaptive systems.
So we're talking about people of the caliber of not only Kalman and Bellman, but also
Simon, who got a Nobel Memorial Prize in economic sciences in 78 for works on dynamic
programming under uncertainty.
And it is around this time that also the concept of dual control theory is being
developed by Feldbaum in Soviet Union.
And also Whittaker, I guess, is around this time that the famous MIT rule is developed.
Maybe you can tell us something about that rule and also what led to, I don't know,
the future developments in the 70s.
Sure, sure. So let's go back to what we talked about as the concept of adaptation,
right? Advantageous confirmation of an organism.
So bring it to the context of a dynamic system.
So here you have a dynamic system, which is the actual, say, aircraft or robot or process
controller or what have you.
And you are monitoring how it's performing.
And then a controller is set in and set in place in closed loop.
And then you design the controller.
So that's what every feedback control system does.
So now the advantageous confirmation here in the context of an adaptive control system
is basically one where you are advantageously adjusting the control parameters in that
control system. So imagine if you had a PID controller, then you're adjusting the PID
gains because what you did at 10,000 feet might be very different from what happens at
30,000 feet and so on.
And so something like a hypersonics flight, which basically covers a large flight
envelope, you do need to have that flexibility in adjusting yourself.
So what do you do then?
What is the response from the environment that you observe?
Then you look at some sort of a performance quantity.
So what we call these days as loss function.
And so you then try to adjust your gains in a way so that you minimize that loss
function.
And so what do you do in order to do that?
You look at something called the gradient.
OK, all right, let's adjust the gains so that when I look at the gradient of this loss
function, then that gives me the indication as to what direction should I adjust.
Is it down or is it up?
And by how much?
And I designed it step size and so on.
So all of those things were basically captured in the MIT rule.
And so who, I mean, yeah, so who basically proposed that particular concept.
So now in parallel, people were trying, beginning to understand about stability
theory, about how to design control systems for systems with nonlinear dynamics.
And so the whole notion of Lyapunov's direct method.
And again, Kalman wrote the seminal paper of how to use that in the design of
nonlinear control systems.
So what people found out soon in the 70s was that this MIT rule, while it's great in
many cases, it sometimes big falls short.
And that is captured by basically tools from stability theory, which says that these
gradient rules are things that do not actually not only not help you, but sometimes
really hurt you because it can actually produce some instabilities if there is a
latency between those performance functions you're measuring and the parameters.
And some of those counter examples basically were brought in.
And so that basically led to adaptive control theory, where you really need to look at
two different kinds of measures and errors in the system.
One is this loss function that you can actually measure, but the other is the
parameters that you're trying to learn and adjust.
And you need to worry about what kind of latencies basically are present between the
time you measure and the time you adjust.
And not all problems can be tackled by just using the gradient alone.
So that basically was sort of the foundation of adaptive control theory.
That's a fantastic way also.
I mean, we talk about a fantastic way to move towards a transition between this brave
era and the era of the 70s, where you mentioned that there is a prominent role of
Lyapunov stability in adaptive control.
We also talked about the fact that most of the research in the brave era was motivated
by supersonic flights.
And it is in this time that there are many successful flights, actually, that produce
incredible results, I would say, in avionics.
Maybe we can hear an excerpt of a video that is taken from those years.
Of course.
Yeah.
The crew cameraman in one of the chase planes gets difficult and dramatic coverage of the
smoothly executed landing.
Crossfield is uninjured, but the X-15, one of three in the X-15 research program, sustains
minor repairable damage.
Crossfield checks his bird, which prior to this incident had made several successful
glide and powered flights.
Soon the X-15 will be released from contractor demonstrations, and research flights will
begin by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and the United States Air Force.
So this excerpt testifies the success of adaptive control, I would say, in practice in the field
of avionics.
The problem is that in 1967, unfortunately, things didn't unfold so well in the test of
a flight that Michael Adams was conducting for NASA, I believe.
That's correct.
He was testing the X-15-3 airplane.
And yeah, unfortunately, things didn't go so well in that scenario.
Michael Adams is known as the first American space mission fatality by the American convention.
He was also the first qualified astronaut because he flew above 50 miles for some period
of time before, unfortunately, his aircraft broke apart.
And maybe we can dig into that.
There is a delightful paper on the Control Systems magazine that you wrote about this
accident.
And I don't know.
So what happened and what were the problems from the point of view of adaptive control?
So I would certainly defer the details of what happened to the paper.
So we do get into that in detail.
But in a sense, what really happened was that there was a one of the there were several
control loops that they had, one of which was had this adaptive capability where there
was a control gain that toggled between two different values based on the content of the
frequency content of a performance measure that they were looking at.
And if depending upon the frequency content, it was either a smaller value or a larger
value, I forget which.
And that was the algorithm.
So you see, in a sense, it's a very simple concept.
I mean, the concept of adaptation is very simple.
You want something and based on what you what you want, you adjust something.
Now, you don't really if you if you're not aware of the complexity of what that means
to the system, then you can get into trouble.
And that's exactly what happened, because you see what you're doing is you're measuring
something and then you're adjusting the parameter.
Now, interestingly enough, I think this I should direct the discussion to Feldbaum's
dual control. Now, what should that parameter be for a given environmental situation?
So in order to really understand that and learn the parameters, you need to go into
estimation. And now that takes infinite time.
Now, in order to really make sure that your performance converges to the right value,
that takes infinite time.
That's control. Now, if you're trying to do both simultaneously, then you can get into
trouble because you're trying to adjust the gains and based on the error and the error
will depend upon the gains.
And so there is a loop circularity here.
And that's exactly what happened, because it turns out that what the situation was, was
not something that really fell neatly into either use this value A1 or A2, but something
else. And that's something that was whatever that new value was, was not learned by the
controller. And because it didn't really learn that value properly, it led into basically
instability because what you have now is a nonlinear control system.
And that had a behavior which led to the closed loop system having unbounded solutions.
So again, here was one where the control practice was way ahead of control theory.
And the awareness that what you really have is a nonlinear control system and it has to
be designed carefully was not there then.
And that's basically what we dug into in the paper.
We said, OK, let's now look at adaptive control because, you know, fast forward to what,
2010 from 1967.
Now we have this understanding of how you should define, design adaptive control
systems, how you can deal with this concept of dual control, where you have this
conflict between infinite time for estimation and infinite time for control.
And you basically break that by introducing appropriate control structures that can make
sure that your performance is well behaved and you have that under control before
learning, before learning.
So you do control first and then with hindsight, you learn the parameters.
That basically is, in a sense, the foundation of adaptive control theory.
It determines a solution to a dynamic system which has uncertainties in real time
without having fully learned what the nonlinear system is.
But what it does is it basically, even with imperfect learning, figures out what the
control system ought to do and so that you can then have the performance in check.
And so what we did in that paper is to basically lay that out and have a correct,
provably correct adaptive controller.
And then we compared it with what was actually implemented in the MH96, which is a
Minneapolis Honeywell 96 controller.
That was the name of that adaptive controller that they had in that fatal flight.
And then we said, OK, let's start to try and compare apples with apples.
And so we started to have a configuration where they looked identical except for, say,
the change in the way in which the parameters were adapted.
And so what we showed was that it was basically the way in which the parameters
were adjusted was incorrect.
And had they really, the awareness of what the overall control system is, had they
done this adjustment according to this rule, then that flight would not have crashed.
So it was a very satisfying experience because it was one of those things where we said,
OK, this is basically what must have happened.
And we were able to replicate that.
And also we could play a what if scenario.
If they had the awareness, this is basically what what they should have done, then
Michael Adams would be here.
I mean, you touched on so many interesting points.
First of all, I want to make sure that the audience knows that there will be links in
the description of this episode to all of the papers that we mentioned.
We're also basing also our story today on a beautiful article written by Anu and
Professor Fratkov on the history of adaptive control.
There will be a link to that paper as well.
There is also an upcoming paper, if I understand correctly, on the interplay between
adaptive control and reinforcement learning.
Yes, it'll appear in the annual reviews in Control Robotics and Automation Systems.
And yeah, the title is exactly that adaptive control and intersections with
reinforcement learning.
There will be a link also to this paper as well.
Of course, in discussing before we touched on, I would say, some very important
points. So the first one that you were mentioning was dual control and essentially
this tension between learning and controlling, which today is what we call the
tradeoff between exploration versus exploitation.
And also, I guess another thing that we should probably mention is that as a result
of this crash, I guess funding was cut short for a short period of time for what
concerns adaptive control.
Is that correct?
Yeah, so certainly people had to regroup and in the specific area of flight control,
there was a pause and efforts to really understand what happened, efforts to
understand control theory, efforts to understand a multivariable control theory.
And so many of those things were set in motion.
And even this whole effort to connect fundamental tenets of stability theory of
nonlinear differential equations with adaptive control, because, you know, the
recognition that what you really are doing when you start to adjust parameters of a
controller in real time makes the whole problem one of a nonlinear time varying
system, a system that is intentionally nonlinear.
So then how do you design those nonlinearities?
And so that's where there was a very elegant connection between adaptive control
design and Lyapunov theory, because Lyapunov theory gives you that guideline as to
how to design the controller such that you make something which is a positive
definite function into a Lyapunov function.
So some of those foundations were in place.
The other very elegant result is it's not something that people talk about a whole
lot these days, but again, in the 70s and the 80s, people explored that quite a bit,
which is a notion of hyperstability and the notion of absolute stability, which
basically is centered on passive systems and strictly passive operators.
And so the whole idea is that if you have, even though they might be nonlinear, then
if you have something which is a strictly passive operator in forward loop, then you
can have several passive operators in feedback loop and structurally the system
will be, will continue to be stable.
So that's why it was called hyperstability.
The notions of absolute stability also are connected with that.
So people like Popov and Aizerman, many of those kinds of really very elegant
stability theories of nonlinear dynamic systems were all sort of brought together.
And this interplay again between parameter adaptation and feedback control were all in
place. And, you know, so then over those two decades, the 70s and the 80s, with these
foundations in place, and then there was another thing to saying, OK, if you really
look at parametric uncertainties, then that gives you the foundation for how to set up
adaptive control systems.
But we also need to look at robustness to nonparametric uncertainties, which might be
in the form of disturbances and model dynamics.
And so I would say in the 90s, the foundations of robust adaptive control were in
place. So this led to introducing terms, which we didn't call it as regularization
then, but it's really ways of regularizing the underlying function, which is convex.
And you really need to make it strongly convex.
And that gives you the robustness.
And that led to a whole bunch of methods based on dead zone, based on what is known as
sigma modification, e-modification, parameter projection.
And all those basically led to this is how you would design a robust adaptive control
system. And so with that now, I say, you know, we should come full circle.
And now coming into the 21st century, there's been actually several successful
demonstrations of advanced flight vehicles with adaptive control, which are actually
in production. And many of these things have been designed by Boeing.
This is something that I didn't know.
I mean, you touched again on so many interesting aspects.
I would like to dissect them a little bit more, all of them, just because it's such a
fascinating story. So again, maybe like moving on from this accident in the 70s, you
mentioned that Lyapunov stability took over somehow.
This is also the time just after 1967 is really the time of also the developments that
led to going on to the moon, essentially.
And so in between, let's say, the 70s and the 80s, stability really played a role.
Lyapunov stability really played a role in adaptive control.
And as you were mentioning, in moving forward towards the 80s, once you have a Lyapunov,
let's say, set up, then it is immediate to ask also the question of robustness of these
methods. Something else that I should mention also before, you know, essentially digging
into this 70s and 80s period is that hyperstability and all of these concepts of
absolute stability as well were coming from the Soviet Union.
And I guess this was also the result of the competition between the US and the Soviets.
I'm not sure about that.
Yeah, you know, yeah.
In fact, when we were writing this paper, Sasha Freitkopf and I were talking about
exactly that, that there's been just so many rich developments, both in the Soviet
Union and the and I guess the Western world.
And many of those things actually happened independently and in parallel.
And in some cases there was a confluence.
So the other interesting place where a fundamental tool that was developed that's
again used very much in adaptive control is what we call as the Kalman-Yakubovich
lemma. And so right there in the name, you can see this sort of parallel development
because separately Kalman and Yakubovich independently came up with this, which is, I
think, one of the really beautiful results because it connects what happens in
analysis in time domain with what happens in frequency domain.
And there are not that many results that basically provide this connection between
these two very different representations of dynamic systems.
And so what they showed basically, and it's one of the central pillars of adaptive
control, because it talks about what kind of performance functions can you use and
adjust the parameters so that even when you don't have access to all of the states in
the dynamic systems, even when the system is partially observable, you still are
guaranteed to have the right adaptation laws.
And so it turns out that the connection between the input-output property of the
dynamic system is basically connected with the existence of a Lyapunov function.
So on the one hand, this input-output stability property is the one in frequency
domain. You can think of it as what kinds of characteristics should that obey in the
frequency domain to the kind of operator that you need to have in time domain that
allows a positive definite function to become a Lyapunov function.
And that, too, is something that happened in the 70s and 80s and was a cornerstone in
the development of adaptive control.
And I would say that the paradigms around those times were essentially two in
adaptive control, model-reference adaptive control, possibly, and self-tuning control.
Can you tell us a bit about the difference of these two paradigms?
Of course, yeah. So you can approach the whole problem by saying, OK, my focus is
really that I want to control the system.
And so at the end of the day, I really don't need to know how a system behaves.
I just need to figure out what I need to do in order to get the performance I want.
So model-reference adaptive control pursued that kind of what we would call as a
direct adaptive control strategy.
Now, on the other hand, if you say, OK, here is a dynamic system, I know how to
control it. But then for whatever reason, something changed in the environment.
And so my parameters have changed.
So now what do I do?
You can look at it completely from the point of view of estimation.
So let's first identify the parameters and then design the controller.
And so this is an explicit estimation, but you can call it as an indirect adaptive
control because first you identify the parameters, then you identify the
controllers. So if you take the notion of separation principle, which is very
elegant and it says, you know what, you don't necessarily need to have observer
design and controller design to, you know, we don't have to worry about the fact
that they are two different steps.
You can actually separate it and have both of them function in parallel and
everything would work out fine.
So the idea was then that, hey, I have this cost function and this cost function
is a regular linear quadratic, you know, it's a quadratic cost.
And so I will optimize this cost.
I will try to come up with a regulator that basically self-tunes itself and
optimizes this cost.
So and I do that by saying, OK, I can estimate the parameters and then basically
use the estimates in the cost function and have that be minimized.
So that was the philosophy taken in the self-tuning regulators.
So and those were the two parallel streams.
And it turned out that if you're going to ensure that even as you're estimating
the cost function is something that remains well behaved, you had to impose
a certain structure to the problem.
And it turned out that some of the assumptions that were made were basically
exactly the same things that you needed to do in order to have the model
reference adaptive controller at B's table.
And so there were a lot of papers written again, I think, towards the end of
the 80s that talked about a unified theory and the similarities between STR
and MRAC and so on.
But you see, it again goes back to the same thing that we talked about earlier
in our conversation, which is this dual control.
Since estimation and control are duals of each other, you really need to have
the right structures for the controller so that even without full estimation,
you can make the controller work.
And at the same time, you also allow those structures to lead to learning of
the parameters, to estimation of the parameters, so that eventually when this
all really is done, after control is completed, after regulation is completed,
you can use what is known as persistent excitation properties of excitation of
the external signals and learn the parameters.
So that was the story behind STR and MRAC.
Thanks for this super nice overview of the two approaches.
Actually, this gives me a nice access to move from the 80s towards the 90s.
This is also the time where I believe you had your PhD as well and where you landed
a super nice paper, essentially, that awarded you the George Axelby Prize, one
of the most important prizes in control theory.
The title of the paper is Robust Adaptive Control in the Presence of Bounded
Disturbances. And I just wanted to talk about this because you mentioned the notion
of persistence of excitation.
And in that paper, you actually show that that plays a fundamental role in adaptive
control, right?
Yes.
So what is the message of the paper?
Right. So we talked about what adaptation is, right?
Advantageous confirmation of an organism now in response to changes in the
environment. So that's very important.
So what is it that you say is your performance function?
So adaptation and even the manifestation of that in an adaptive control system is a
very simple thing.
It's a very — think of it as a very simple-minded entity, because what it's doing
is, hey, here is the performance, here's the loss function, and here is the
parameter. Adjust the parameter in the direction of the gradient.
That minimizes that loss function.
So if you use this framework, then it turns out that you can do very well in
controlling the system and ultimately even estimating the system with persistent
excitation, provided there is a certain kind of a structure in the environment.
Now, if this environment is pristine and is well-behaved and ideal and the only
uncertainty is parametric in nature, then what we are talking about would be
correct. But you are only observing a performance quantity, right?
A loss function.
What if, unbeknownst to you, there were other forces at work, other non-parametric
effects that basically was affecting the performance, and you didn't know that?
So if that happens, then essentially you are trying to adjust the parameters in a
direction that might make that performance well-behaved, but you might end up
destroying something else.
And that basically was what people were observing could happen in adaptive control
systems. You can explain that in many different ways.
I mentioned convexity and making it regularized and making it strongly convex.
That's one way of looking at it.
And the other way of looking at it is here is a convex function.
Then instead of doing regularization, because it introduces other artifacts into
the picture, what if I make it strongly convex by using the notion of persistent
excitation? So that turns out is another way of really looking at the problem.
So then it turns out that even when there are disturbances, this performance
function that you're observing, this loss function that you're observing, can be
utilized in order to keep things in check.
The paper that, if you go back and read that paper written in 86, it really doesn't
have any of the language that I'm using right now, but that's just another way of
looking at it as to how the relation between persistent excitation and robustness
manifests itself. You can think of it in another way.
Nonlinear systems or differential equations are extraordinarily rich compared to
linear differential equations.
The notions that we have of what happens for the unforced system and what happens
in the presence of external forcing inputs is very different between a linear
system and a nonlinear system.
And that basically is what is mentioned in the paper.
If you take a system that is, so there is no external input and you've got a nice
system that's uniformly asymptotically stable, right?
The origin is uniformly asymptotically stable, meaning you shake it, everything
will go back to the origin.
Now you introduce exogenous inputs into the picture.
We know from linear systems that if you have a situation like that, bounded input
will produce a bounded output.
Not so for nonlinear systems.
There is a very nice paper by Varaya, De Sovere and Varaya, I think.
Actually, I have to go back and check the authors.
Certainly it's by De Sovere, maybe the co-author is not Varaya, but someone else
who basically showed this very nice counter example where you have a uniformly
asymptotically stable system.
You put in a bounded input, not only does the output does not remain bounded, it
actually blows up.
So we were able to come up with a counter example very similar to that in the
context of an adaptive control system, which basically showed that if you just
had the simple gradient rule type of thing, and then you introduce a
disturbance, you can actually prove, you can actually come up with a positive
definite function and show that there is a bounded, there is a region, not bounded
region, where if you start there, you will stay there forever.
And it's an open invariant region.
And so the trajectory, it actually blows up.
So what it says is that things may not actually, it's not easy to show stability,
but it actually becomes unstable.
Fortunately, there was also a happy ending to that paper, which says that this
might happen if you don't have enough persistent excitation.
So not only do you need persistent excitation, but you need enough of it.
So sort of a signal to noise ratio type of condition.
And if that is satisfied, then you get bounded input, bounded output for
nonlinear systems, which is why that paper, I think, is very special.
Very quick comment about this, this fact that you mentioned on the level, if you
want, of persistence of excitation, because from my very humble perspective, it
seems that these notions are now coming back in vogue in these times, at least at
major conferences in control.
But yeah, as you mentioned, from the 80s to the 90s, we start moving our horizon, if
you want, in adaptive control towards issues of robustness and nonlinear systems,
essentially. So that's the way I read the history, at least of adaptive control.
So I would like maybe to shift towards those years and maybe even with a look
towards our current times.
So what happened, let's say, between the 90s towards the 2000s and 2010s, maybe?
Oh, there's, you know, it's hard to sort of single out any specific sort of
direction. So just like, you know, in general, what happened in the rest of the
control systems branches, adaptive control tools started looking at nonlinear
systems, different kinds of nonlinearities, multivariable systems, distributed
adaptive controllers, looking at what happens when there are time delays and what
happens when you're trying to implement adaptive control in cyber-physical systems
and what's the right way to allocate the computation to different kinds of
components in a real-time embedded system.
And of course, you know, applications, what exactly is the kind of uncertainties
that are typically present in applications?
For instance, in a flight controller, you say, OK, here is a system dynamics, even
though, let's say, XR equals AX plus BU, A and B are unknown.
Let's parse that a little bit more carefully.
What exactly is unknown in a dynamic system?
Because it's not as if you know nothing about A and B and then you start designing
K. There's a lot of information.
And so one of the things that sort of, you know, came into, that people had better
understanding of as time went on, for instance, you know, wind tunnel tests are
things that are very carefully employed before designing a flight control system.
So there's a lot of information in the dynamics.
So based on, you know, aerodynamics, understanding of the equations of motion,
conservation equations, and I'm putting it in a very simplified way, A is not really
unknown. There's a lot of information in A.
Now, on the other hand, B matrix, that's a very different story.
It's not often that you know everything about it because it has to do with the way
in which control surfaces interact with the aerodynamics.
And not only that, control surfaces, you know, have many different components to it.
From the time you actually have the information coming from your controller and
then goes into the appropriate computational structures and then goes into this thing
called the actuator and then the actuator basically provides, say, for instance, the
control moments and forces, there's a lot that goes on.
And in that whole chain of events, there can be a lot of uncertainty.
So sometimes it's not that A is unknown.
There are specific aspects to B, B times U, that basically can have uncertainty.
So then you see, here you have this very generic theory, but then you have to
systematically break it down and figure out how it should be applied.
So many of those developments also happened as the years went by.
So and then how do you actually, you know, scale the whole problem up?
So one of the things that papers that we wrote was on a multivariable control
system, which was for a very flexible aircraft, which had something like, oh, I
don't know, 700 state variables and 33 control inputs and 300 or so outputs.
And so, you know, that's then it had several parameters that we were adjusting
and we showed that in real time you could do all of those things.
So, you know, many of these kinds of developments, I would say, are probably
what occupied the attention and is still occupying the attention of researchers
in the adaptive control community.
And maybe not to, of course, it will not be possible to cover everything in the
span of just one hour or a little more.
So we'll definitely do some injustice to some researchers in adaptive control.
But something that I really want to touch on is the connection between adaptive
control and essentially reinforcement learning or modern machine learning.
I found in reading this beautiful history paper that you wrote together with
Professor Fraktov, that there was an article by Richard Sutton, Andrew Bartow
and Ronald Williams on the Control Systems Magazine.
So literally speaking to a control audience where the title is literally
reinforcement learning is direct adaptive optimal control.
So I found it incredibly funny because they're now regarded as pioneers in the
field of reinforcement learning.
And they were telling us that what they're doing is direct adaptive optimal control.
Yeah.
So essentially in 2016, we all know that AlphaGo made a splash by beating Lee Sedol,
the champion on the game of Go.
And therefore there was a huge resurgence in interest, if you want, on
reinforcement learning.
What is the interplay now?
What is the status?
Right.
Oh, that's a very hard question to answer in the time that we have.
Again, just like the one I would certainly like to defer the listener to the recent
article that I mentioned that will appear in the annual reviews, Controls, Robotics
and Automation for details.
But, you know, the two fields, reinforcement learning and adaptive control, have
evolved differently with different tools and more importantly, different objectives.
And the problems formulation statement in the two fields, they also vary.
So what is adaptive control saying?
Adaptive control is saying that I have a dynamic system.
And right now, right now, there is an uncertainty.
Or, you know, imagine again, let's consider a flight platform, right?
A quadrotor.
It's a drone.
It's flying and it's in mid-flight.
And then something goes wrong.
It's in mid-flight.
And then right now, in real time, something goes wrong.
You don't have time to do experiments and do a lot of simulations.
And, oh, what if I were to use this policy, then what would it do?
You just don't have the time.
And so you directly have to adapt and you have to figure out on the fly, what kind
of thrust do I give to those motors in order to have it still do its thing,
whatever it might be, hover, follow a particular flight path.
So the emphasis is on coming up with a solution in real time.
So because of that, adaptive control is geared towards what
happened and what is happening.
So it looks at the past and the present.
Now, when you go into reinforcement learning, the trajectory there evolved
from a point of view of optimality.
So even let's take that, the game, the chess or a goal, you have to figure out
what your policy is that needs to happen now and in the future.
So you're looking at the present and the future, and you're trying to be optimal
in terms of what the policy is that you're going to take so that
you can beat your opponent.
Now, you can see that distinctly, they have two different points of view.
Past and present is really what you're looking at in adaptive control, simply
because of the problem statement.
And again, present and future is what you're looking at simply
So necessarily they deployed different disparate tools in
order to realize their objective.
However, both of them have a common feature, which is that both of them are
trying to deal with problems that have uncertainties in them.
But it's just that when you go in and start unpacking it and go into the
details, the statements that are being made and the tools that need to be
employed start becoming different.
And so this is why when you start to apply RL to problems in dynamic systems,
which have uncertainties, I think one needs to be careful in figuring out what
exactly are the different kinds of things that are under your disposal.
If indeed you have time to make the decisions of exploration, then you have
time before you start figuring out when you start your exploitation.
Exploration here is parameter learning.
Exploitation here is control.
I mean, though, if you go into the details, I'm sure there are different
shades and nuances, but for the sake of discussion, suppose you do that.
Then if you're in real time, you don't have time to explore.
You really have to control first before you can learn.
So then control comes before learning.
So those are the kinds of things where adaptive control and reinforcement
learning differ and have different kinds of strengths and weaknesses.
There's no question that there is a lot of tools that we can do in machine
learning that help us deal with unstructured environments, large data
sets, huge number of agents.
So many of those lessons and successes that have been illustrated in algorithms,
we should start to figure out how we can combine that with tools that
are used in adaptive control.
From the same point of view, adaptive control basically has lots of dos and
don'ts for very good reasons, like, you know, this whole concept that we keep
talking about of duality between estimation and control.
Sometimes you have to put control before learning.
You do control first and then you learn with hindsight.
So you have to make sure that even when you have, there's sometimes you don't
have enough information to have perfect learning.
So in that case, you cannot do the indirect control.
You cannot fully learn the parameters before you do control.
And there's another thing about, you know, the title direct, adaptive, optimal
control, that's very difficult to do.
Again, because of what I said, which is what is difficult to do, adaptive
and optimal at the same time.
The reason is exactly because of what I said earlier.
You, you are now looking at the past and the present, and you need to fix that
first before you can start looking into the future.
So I firmly believe, and that's one of the things that I think is mentioned in
the paper, that is this sort of adapt, learn, optimize triad that I think we
need to think about.
So first you adapt, then you learn with hindsight.
And then now that you've learned, you go ahead and optimize.
And that kind of a sequence sometimes is inevitable.
That's fantastic point of view.
Fantastic.
Um, essentially in the last few moments, you also addressed one of the questions
that I wanted to ask you, which was what can the two fields teach to one another?
So I'll ask you another one.
And that's, what are you most excited about for the years to come?
Uh, how do you envision say emerging worlds like those of machine learning
where now we're really heading towards, uh, from translating speech into actions
or speech into images and the world of, uh, adaptive control.
Uh, what, what do you see?
Oh, I think we've just scratched the surface.
There's just so much to do.
And I hope that the younger, younger generation will continue to do that
because I, I don't know how much more time I'll, I'll have myself to continue
to, you know, chip away at this.
I mean, computationally the world has changed so much, even, you know, over
the last, uh, 20 years, what we used to think of as, uh, methods that are, oh
my God, that's going to be impossible to do are now not just possible.
It's a cakewalk.
So that kind of a, sort of a breakdown of the, the, the blinders that we used to put
for ourselves, Oh, this is computationally.
Okay.
But this one, Oh, come on.
That's never going to be possible is not, is that boundary is changing so much.
I mean, still, I think there are some challenges in terms of, I mean, like for
instance, why is adaptive MPC not here yet?
Because even that as competent, uh, even with the computational resources, still,
I don't think we are there to figure out how you can do the adaptation
and optimization at the same time.
So trying to figure out how you can leverage the kind of computational
resources that you have in figuring out what needs to happen offline.
And what needs to happen online is I think the challenge.
How do you make sure that you address the sim to real gap?
How do you make sure that you leverage all of the things that you learned
offline and keep that, uh, transport them into an online construct?
This interplay is, I think, becoming very complex.
And that is, I think the boundary that we have to navigate and, uh, figure
it out and tease apart as we go forward.
I think there's so much to do there.
And again, one of the biggest things that has to happen is more dialogue
and more conversations and more collaborations between the two
communities, which is beginning to happen.
So not necessarily just more computation, but also more theory, more dialogue.
Okay.
Um, maybe, you know, moving towards the end of our conversation
there's a couple of questions that I tend to ask to everyone that features
on the show, one of them is about advice to future generations.
So if there is anything that you would have liked to know before starting
your career, was there anything that you would advise, say to current
students or even future students?
Um, I think you need to figure out how you can be extremely good at one
thing and very good at many things.
It's not easy to do.
You have to have a mainstay that where, you know, and that's what, if you think
about, if you're a doctoral student, that's exactly what a PhD is, right?
That you are going to be the expert.
Um, or I mean, not just one of the experts in that particular area and
you're intimately familiar with that, right?
That's what I mean by that.
But I think the, the specialty is becoming, it needs to happen
even along with many other things.
And so the breakdown between what you're doing in your area and it's, it's
interrelation with the other domains is becoming a lot more complex.
And so compared to, I think what it used to be maybe 20, 30 years ago,
the, the awareness and the understanding of how to converse with other
transdisciplinary partners becoming more and more important, um, you know,
controls is changing a lot.
It's no longer a feedback control of a single device or a single system.
It's no longer control of a large scale system is no longer control of
a large scale engineer systems.
It's really things that control is present and needed in a societal scale.
So, which means that you really start to, you need to start thinking about
what does it mean, this concept and this very broad canvas.
How do you apply that in the context of say, for instance, energy justice,
which is a totally different domain, but still there is a notion of here
is a system, here's a performance, here's ways you monitor it and develop
metrics, and here's how you mitigate something, right?
So in order to do all of those things, it seems to me that in addition to being
very good, excellent at one thing, you really need to do at least one thing
where you're completely out of your comfort zone.
And, you know, I think you should do that activity where you're so scared.
Like you, I know nothing about it, but I think it's very important to immerse
ourselves in that endeavor and you learn that thing.
And so that I think gives you the ability to, to really understand
controls and in its essence and in a very broad way.
I mean, for instance, I know you didn't quite ask this question,
but let me answer that anyway.
In our lab, there are sort of two thrusts in my, you know, the active
adaptive control lab at MIT.
One is to do develop control in a very deep sense and look at adaptive
control, you know, and its intersections with machine learning.
The other thrust is in trying to implement control in a very broad
sense and to look at ways in which the whole notion of how you collect
information and implement decisions in a large scale system, say, for instance,
in power grids or in transportation or in other sort of endeavors that you
wouldn't normally think of in terms of what a control is, you know, in a
non-engineered sense in a societal scale system.
So I think having this kind of two pronged attack, I think is very useful.
That's fantastic.
Actually, apologies for not touching on the huge endeavor also that you're
having in the field of smart grids.
That's another major line of research of yours.
And actually I'll put a link to a couple of papers in the description, just for
people who are interested in this topic and in ANUS research.
Just to finish on the topic of future generations, I'm curious whether do you
have some kind of secret sauce for when you feel stuck or, I mean, it's something
that happens a lot for PhD students and in general to any researcher, I would say.
So what is your approach to that feeling?
Yeah, no, I mean, research is all about figuring out how to even realize that
you're stuck and, you know, to get unstuck.
One of the things I learned from my advisor, Professor Narendra, is how to have
the intellectual courage to completely scrap what you're doing and start from
with a clean slate.
Don't try to tweak things and say, OK, all right, maybe you should.
No, no, no, no.
Just pull back and have the courage to just completely chuck everything that you
might have been doing either for the past week or a past month or even a past
year and say, start from scratch.
OK, what is it that you're trying to do?
So starting with a fresh slate, blank slate, clean slate, and really regroup.
And OK, what is that problem?
And to zoom out and ask questions at a very high level and again start zooming
in helps enormously.
But for to do that, you should have the courage to chuck what you're doing because
it's like, oh, my God, I've put so much effort into it and I have all this
information and knowledge.
Yes, you do.
But believe me, it will help you.
But don't be straightjacketed with what you're facing right now.
I found and that's something I learned from Professor Narendra and that has served
me again and again extremely well.
Well, you're serving me a fantastic assist for another question that I ask to
everyone else that features on your show.
And that's who were the most influential figures in your careers?
If you had to name three, who would they be?
Definitely, I would start with Professor Narendra.
I have learned so much from him how to be a researcher, how to figure out how to
pick problems and how never to really give up.
And that enthusiasm and that optimism is something that I learned from him.
Other than that, I don't know if there is, I would say it's directly because of
interaction with any specific individual.
But, you know, all of Kalman's work have been, you know, enormously
inspirational and sort of mind boggling.
Where did this come?
I mean, like I was talking about Kalman Yakovlevich's lemma, right?
Where did that come from?
How did they even think to sort of connect some very two disparate things
from input-output property to a Lyapunov function?
I have learned a lot from that.
And the other, again, works of that, and I began to know about Pravin Varaya
only and started interacting with them much, much later.
But again, his papers, too, I found have been enormously educational and
inspirational in terms of how you can, and there is something that is
attributed to him in terms of what they call is a folk theorem about
optimization in power grids.
And I find that to be a seminal work that sort of brings in elements of
analysis into something that really was groundbreaking in the context of
constraint optimization in power grids.
So I would mention, I guess, those three individuals.
Yeah.
Thanks for this.
In closing, maybe the last question I want to ask you is out of curiosity,
on a more personal level.
Do you have any like favorite pastime or, and I don't know, do you like reading?
Do you like any specific type of exercise or anything like that?
Oh yeah, no, I like to read a lot.
I'm more partial to fiction than nonfiction.
So I always have at least one book on iPad to read and one physical book to read.
So, you know, about anything and everything, I mean, I'm part of three
different book clubs and, and, you have any three books to recommend to the
audience, like your favorite books ever?
Um, well, uh, the book Thief, um, uh, Cutting for a Stone, those are older.
And the one, the most recent one I read was Cloud Cuckoo Land, which is
absolutely fantastic, all actually very incisive portrayals of humanity
and interrelationships.
Yeah.
Well, Anu, it's been a pleasure to have you on the show.
It's been really a fantastic ride.
Um, thank you for being here and thanks for taking the time to join us.
It's been my pleasure.
Absolute pleasure.
Thank you for having me here.
Thank you for listening.
I hope you liked the show today.
If you enjoyed the podcast, please consider giving us five stars on Apple
Podcasts, follow us on Spotify, support on Patreon or PayPal, and connect
with us on social media platforms.
See you next time.