Hello and welcome to In Control, the first podcast on control theory.
Here we discuss the science of feedback, decision making, artificial intelligence and much more.
I'm your host Alberto Padoan, live from a recording studio in Zurich.
Big thanks to our sponsor, the National Centre of Competence in Research of Dependable Ubiquitous
Automation and the International Federation of Automatic Control.
Our guest today is Mustafa Kammasch, Professor of Control Theory and Systems Biology in the
Department of Biosystems Science and Engineering at ETH Zurich.
Welcome to the show, Mustafa.
Glad to be here.
Thanks for having me at your podcast, Alberto.
Mustafa, let's jump right into it.
What is cyber genetics?
Cyber genetics is actually a portmanteau of two words, cybernetics and genetics.
And it's a term I came up with a few years ago because I got tired of saying all the
time research at the interface of systems and control theory and genetic engineering.
So it just seems much more fun and much more compact to just say cyber genetics.
So essentially it is just that, it's a fusion of cybernetics, which is the term coined by
Norbert Wiener in 1948, which aims to study control and communication in the human and
in the machine under the same umbrella.
And it has a more modern feature, which is the genetics part.
As you see, at the time of Norbert Wiener, 1948, the structure of DNA hasn't even been
discovered yet.
And so much of the work that went on in cybernetics had more to do with things like neuroscience,
maybe diseases that had to do with neuromuscular sources.
But nowadays we have much more powerful tools.
We have much more powerful genetic tools and we could do so much more.
And so you can imagine now we can bring this cybernetics to a new level.
So that's what I mean when I say cyber genetics.
Yeah, that's a fantastic definition.
I might ask, what is a gene actually?
What do we mean by that?
And what do we mean by genetics?
What are the goals there?
Yeah, I think a gene is essentially the basic hereditary units.
You know, very simply, you can think of a gene as corresponding to a single protein.
It's not exactly like that.
It's not always like that, but I think this is good enough.
And so each gene is a stretch of DNA encoded using nucleotides on DNA.
And when that stretch is expressed, the outcome is a single protein.
This protein goes on to interact with other proteins or maybe with other genes to implement
various different functions.
I guess there it would be useful to have a small primer on how biology works and how
DNA is used in biology or in biological systems.
Yeah, so of course DNA is central to life.
In its sequences are encoded, you know, all the biological functions that the organism
requires.
It's extremely dense with information.
And so you can think about DNA as encoding all the information needed for the biological
processes required for life.
But it's not only a storage device, because DNA itself is a molecule and it interacts
with other proteins through which this interaction regulates the amount of gene expression.
So gene expression is a term that comes up repeatedly, and you mentioned something about
it.
So it consists of two different processes.
The first one is transcription, and the second one is translation.
So transcription is the process by which the DNA is read inside the cell.
And the outcome of this transcription process is messenger RNA.
So you have a messenger RNA that then goes on to be translated by cellular machines called
ribosomes, and the outcome of that process, of that translation process, is these proteins.
Usually you have a sequence of amino acids that then folds into a secondary structure
or a tertiary structure, and once it's fully folded, then it's called a protein, and that's
when it's functional.
And by functional, I mean, you know, it can interact with other proteins, with other RNAs,
with other genes, to do all the wonderful things that the cell has to do to exist.
I guess that maybe at this point already, someone in the audience will think, am I listening
to the right podcast?
But you mentioned so many words that come from engineering.
So you mentioned regulation, you mentioned machines, you literally called ribosomes machines,
you mentioned interaction, which is so key in our field.
So what is the role of control theory here, and what does it have to do with biology?
Actually, control is very native to biology.
In fact, biological systems discovered control billions of years before we did,
and they have been employing it in different flavors, different levels of organization,
much longer than we have.
And so it's not really an exaggeration to say that much of the complexity of biological
systems have to do with the requirements of regulation.
And that's because regulation, or what biologists call regulation, what we also call control,
exists at every level of organization in biology, from the molecular level, to the cellular level,
to the tissue level, to the organism level, even to the ecological level.
And so if you look at the typical biological systems, you will very quickly find tons and
tons of feedback loops, feedforward loops that are helping the cells achieve their various
functions in a very robust fashion.
So really, it's quite natural to be doing control in biology, because as I said, much
of the complexity of biology is about regulation.
Or comes from this regulation.
Yeah.
And I was actually looking at your biography, you know, in doing my homework for this podcast,
and you're natively a control theorist, but you then moved, ventured, if you want, in
this field.
And so I was wondering what has drawn your attention from being a very theoretical person
who was working into deep questions in robust control towards this fascinating field?
Yeah, that's a very good question.
Actually, thinking back at those times, this was in the late 90s.
So I was working on robust control for my PhD thesis, and the early and mid into the
late 90s, I was still working on robust control.
But by that time, really, the main problems in robust control have been solved.
So the H-infinity problems, state space solutions, Turicati equation problem has been solved.
And there wasn't much left in terms of, you know, big problems.
And at the same time, around the same time, my wife had our second child.
And after childbirth, she had the problems with her thyroid gland.
So she was going through a period of hyperthyroidism and hypothyroidism.
So the thyroid hormones were essentially oscillating like crazy.
And I had no idea what was going on.
So I went to the library and I picked up a textbook on endocrinology.
Endocrinology is a science of hormones and their actions.
And really, this was a very transformative moment because I was shocked by what I was
reading.
Everything in that book seemed like it's a control theory without equations, right?
So there's one exquisite feedback loop after the other, doing all kinds of different things,
but of course, no equations.
So I was really fascinated by this.
And that led me to go to the National Animal Disease Center at Iowa State University, where
I was at the time in the US.
And I talked to one of the physiologists and I said, you know, I'm a control theorist.
Please, can you give me a problem where you think control theory could be useful?
And it was very naive, but actually, it turned out he gave me a fantastic problem.
He gave me a problem that he was working on that had to do with how mammals, in his particular
case, dairy cows, regulate their blood calcium.
So us humans and other mammals, we have a very tight regulation of calcium in the blood
plasma.
This is important because calcium ions are needed for muscle function, nerve function,
blood clotting, signal communications, and so on.
So it's a very important biochemical role.
And because of that, we have evolved a very elaborate control system to maintain the
concentration at about 9 milligrams per deciliter.
So it's really a fascinating problem, and it could have been a better problem to start
with.
In that case, they were looking at a specific disease that dairy cows had that humans don't
usually have.
It's called milk fever.
And it turned out to be some kind of a dynamic instability in the closed-loop system that
was induced by the way humans breed cows to make more and more and more milk.
And so myself and another young master's students that I had, we had a lot of fun
working out the details.
And when all the dust settled, we had discovered that mammals regulate their blood calcium
by using proportional integral feedback.
It's as simple as that.
So that was kind of a nice discovery.
All the ingredients and the elements were there in terms of the main players, the hormones
and their interactions.
It just waited for somebody with a control perspective to explain what these interactions
were actually doing.
Well, you probably didn't have any mathematical model for studying this phenomenon, or was
there actually any?
Did you have to develop everything from scratch?
We didn't have any mathematical model, but we developed a very, very simple model, actually.
Just looking at the blood volume as a constant volume and looking at various sources for
calciums and various sinks, and then making simple arguments like, you know, disturbance
looks like an outflux of calcium.
And then we know the system regulates with zero steady-state tracking error, so the
controller must have such and such properties.
And so the model we used actually was very simple, maybe a second-order model.
Only when we were looking at the specific disease did we have to go to more complicated
nonlinearities.
And even then, there were saturation-type nonlinearities, which were very naturally
justified based on the nature of the disease that we were working with.
So basically, third-order linear systems with saturation nonlinearities.
That was sufficient to explain the whole story.
Of course, one can develop more complicated models with different compartments and so
on, but I think for the purposes that we needed it, this was sufficient.
And the essence was there.
And so that was your, let's say, initial start in this world of systems and synthetic
biology.
Actually, may I ask, what is the difference between the two fields, between synthetic
biology and systems biology?
That's a very good question.
I get asked this question a lot.
I think, you know, one analogy would be it's similar to the difference between system theory
and control theory.
So systems biology aims to analyze existing biological networks, and it's some kind of
reverse engineering, if you will.
So you have a network that's functional, you have a cell that's doing a certain thing,
you're trying to understand why it does what it does.
And when it fails, why it fails.
And so you kind of ask questions about a network that already exists.
Now, synthetic biology does things a little bit differently.
So it's more like a forward engineering.
How can we modify this network?
How can we add additional components so that it either achieves new function or it fixes
the function that somehow was broken, right?
So if there's a disease and then you add a new element into your cells to kind of cure
that disease, this would be more on the forward engineering part.
So I think that's really the main difference.
It's like adding the synthesis aspect to a systems biology.
In our language, the former would be analysis, dealing with analysis, and the second would
be dealing with design.
So they go hand in hand, they're complementary.
That's a very good way of saying it.
Also, synthetic biology can be used for analysis.
So for example, let's say you have a hypothesis about a biological system, you think it works
in a certain way, and then you go build it in the lab.
And if it doesn't function the way it's supposed to function, then you have to adjust
your understanding.
And so one can also think of synthetic biology as sort of a field that allows you to tinker
and get a deeper understanding of the underlying science, not only just to build new things.
And this is reminiscent of another Feynman quote, building his understanding that appeared
on this podcast before.
Yeah.
What I cannot build, I do not understand.
Exactly, exactly.
Exactly, yeah.
That's an often quoted quote by Richard Feynman, a synthetic biologist.
Yeah.
I think it captures the essence quite well.
Actually, yeah, I was looking at the history of synthetic biology, and it seems to be extremely
recent, at least, you know, the year 2000 seems to be the turning point in this field.
Of course, there are predecessors, but in 2000, there were, I believe, three really
milestone papers on nature where people actually implemented biological circuits that essentially
implemented a switch.
Another one would implement an oscillator, and another circuit would implement a feedback
mechanism, essentially.
So all three in the same year.
It's incredible.
That's right.
Even in the same journal.
Exactly right.
So there were three milestone papers that essentially demonstrated what you said.
One can think of these circuits in the following way.
One of them used one gene, and the second one used two genes, and the third one used
three genes, and they all had negative feedback.
So when you have negative feedback with one gene, you have an auto-regulatory circuit,
so that's the usual feedback systems that we like.
When you have two genes, each having negative feedback on each other, you have positive
feedback, and that's what implements, by stability in this case, a toggle switch.
And the third had, you know, three genes, each repressing the other in a sort of a
ring-type fashion.
So then you get a ring oscillator.
And yeah, that's a work of Michael Elowitz.
Those are the three classic papers that kicked the field into motion.
And in fact, the tools of synthetic biology, genetic engineering, the most important tool,
they were already available in the 70s and 80s, and many biologists actually have done
synthetic constructs.
But I think in the year 2000, people were thinking of this field more like VLSI circuit
design, right?
So you can build circuits and devices that then you can put together into functional
units.
And this is a distinctly engineering approach.
It's no longer just tinkering with one gene or another to see what happens, but it's
actually with a purpose to build more complex systems.
And here we are, what, 23 years later, and, you know, we're still struggling with a lot
of these designs.
We can build more complicated circuits now.
Instead of one or two genes, we can build circuits with tens of genes.
But there's still lots of challenges.
So I think the field is still in its infancy.
A huge promise, of course, but lots of challenges.
So I think for researchers who want to work in this field, I think this is a very good
time to be doing it.
There's a lot to unpack in what you just mentioned.
I don't know where to start.
One of the things that made me think when you were elaborating on your thoughts was
that you touched on so many elementary components that are very familiar to the area of
computing.
So switches, oscillators.
So in hearing about these concepts, what I think about is a computer.
So it seems like it's possible to assemble some sort of biological computer out of those
components.
The second thing that I'm extremely excited about is what we can actually do with these
circuits.
So the ones that you just mentioned and what is actually the time horizon in which we can
hope to see something, let's say, in our lifetime.
Is it going to be in two centuries, a millennia?
Who knows?
And the third thing that I would like to ask you is what are the main developments in the
middle, let's say from 2000 to today?
So what happened in between?
Okay, so starting from the last part of your question, so what happened in between?
I think that what happened is people started to build more complex circuits.
And in the process, they ran into challenges.
So there are various challenges when you're working with biological substrates that one
does not find when working with electric circuits.
Interestingly, a lot of people working in this field, synthetic and systems, synthetic
biology in particular, have a background in physics or engineering and so on.
So the electric circuit analogy has been a running theme throughout.
And I think while this analogy had served the field well early on, I don't personally
think it's any longer a useful analogy to continue to pursue for reasons we can discuss
if you want.
But the idea there was, you know, you want to modularize everything.
So you want to build functional units that then you can combine together with other units
in series or in parallel and be able to scale up that way.
But biology didn't play well with this vision.
There are many issues.
For example, when you're doing electric circuits, communication or information is
transmitted through conduits, wires that are very, very precise, and only the parts
that talk to each other generally talk to each other, right?
I mean, of course, you could have electromagnetic interference and so on, but most circuits
don't have these issues.
In biology, it's not like this.
You know, all the molecules see all the other molecules.
So the way you would transmit information is through specificity.
You know, molecule A binds to molecule B.
Maybe it binds molecule C a little bit, but really it's molecule B that it needs to
interact with.
So you end up with a lot of crosstalk like this.
So that's one problem.
Another problem is noise or stochasticity.
So when you're working with electric circuits, you have your Ohm's law, you have your
ordinary differential equations, or, you know, everything is more or less deterministic.
Of course, one can still talk about shot noise and so on at various frequencies.
But in biology, it's not like this at all.
So molecules very often come in very low copy numbers.
So you have one gene, for example, a handful of mRNAs, and these interactions between these
low copy numbers species, they're random in nature.
Molecule A interacts with molecule B only if they happen to bind, collide with each
other.
But maybe in the process or before that happens, molecule A interacts with molecule C first,
and then some other reaction takes place.
So really, the timing and order of chemical reactions when you have very low copy numbers
is random.
So this should be compared with what you've learned in chemistry in high school, where
things are present in very large copy numbers, Avogadro's numbers in a test tube, where
none of this is true.
So you can actually approximate or you can safely describe the dynamics using ordinary
differential equations.
They're nonlinear, but, you know, that come from mass action kinetics or other type of
kinetics.
But in the end of the day, you get deterministic equations that represent continuous variables
that describe the different concentrations of the different reactions, but not so inside
the living cell where the copy numbers is low and the randomness is ever present.
So a more suitable tool in this case is to look at, instead of continuous variables that
evolve deterministically, you look at stochastic or random variables to represent the number
of molecules for each of the different proteins or RNAs and the stochastic nature in which
these random variables evolve.
So really, the typical model that we work with in this case is a continuous time discrete
state Markov process, and that's a much better representation of what's going on inside
the living cell, especially when you have very low copy numbers.
So noise is another big problem that one has to deal with.
Of course, nonlinearity as well, because everything is nonlinear when you have chemical reactions.
And so a wealth of mathematical as well as computational problems to deal with.
Yeah.
So what you just said, essentially you replied to a question that I wanted to ask you, which
would be what are the challenges in controlling biomolecular systems?
And to me, it seems like the scale in a way determines also the way you describe the processes
that you're interested.
As you said, there seems to be a fundamental difference between electrical circuits and
biomolecular, if you want, systems.
So, and I wonder what is the role of control engineering there?
So what can we hope to achieve?
What is the current progress there?
And where are we going towards?
I mean, I think I don't want to give the impression that one must only use these stochastic models,
otherwise nothing works.
Because depending on the problem that you're looking at and the scale that you're looking
at, very often deterministic ordinary differential equations can still serve as good models for
biological phenomena.
Just one has to be careful that when you're looking inside the cell, especially smaller
cells like bacteria, this assumption may be violated and you may end up with behaviors
that are very different.
Very often, actually, the most suitable approach is a hybrid one, where you have some variables
that are stochastic and discrete, others are continuous and evolved deterministically,
and they interact with each other.
So, you know, this is probably the most useful model.
So what control problems exist?
Even if one sticks to the deterministic framework, and let's talk about this first, the issues
that I mentioned before, crosstalk is one of them, you would like to do regulation,
you'd like to regulate certain variables, and these variables, for example, must track
certain set points or reject certain disturbances, so you end up with a control problem.
You know, how do you design a feedback or feedforward mechanism that will implement
this or that would meet these control specifications?
So what is so challenging about biology?
Well, for one thing, again, we're sticking even to deterministic descriptions, all the
variables are positive variables.
So whatever you want to do, it has to be done with positive quantities, right?
So positive systems.
I mean, that's one of the main challenges.
The functions that you build, the controllers that you have to synthesize, you cannot just
write a transfer function and just say, please build me this transfer function, you know,
or this nonlinear function.
You are constrained by chemical reactions.
So everything that you want to implement, your controller, for example, has to be implementable
using biochemical reactions, right?
So that also adds a second constraint.
And it's the interplay of these two constraints, the positivity of the variables plus the
constraints that are imposed by the type of interactions you can have inside a living
cell, I think give biology the distinctive flavor that it has.
And it opens up a wealth of problems in control theory.
What kind of controllers can you build using these chemical reactions?
How would you achieve, let's say, perfect tracking, robust steady state tracking with
these type of controllers and these type of networks?
They have to be positive, they have to be implementable, realizable as a chemical reaction.
Can you realize any transfer function, or can you approximate it using biochemical reactions?
So there's really a wealth of problems that control theory can contribute to.
And I'm not saying that existing control theory can address these things, and that's really
the beauty of this, is that it's not just, you know, here, I'm just going to move the
methods that people have already developed in our field and just apply them to control
theory, to biology.
That would be the wrong approach.
I think one has to be open-minded, and you look at the problems that emerge in biology,
and more often than not, you have to develop a new control theory that is suited for biology.
And I think that's even more fun that way.
So that's what we do in my lab.
We try to develop a control theory, a new foundation for control theory at the molecular
scale, and then we also try to build these chemical reaction mechanisms using genetic
engineering tools.
And so I think for me, at least, the challenging part is also the most fun and interesting
part, is where the theory and the experiments meet.
The theoretical questions are motivated by the experimental considerations, and the experiments
we do are always guided or informed by the theory we develop.
And there's this interaction, very close interaction, that I think is just, you know,
every time theory impacts the experiment, I really get a kick out of this in the lab.
And I think that's sitting at the boundary between the experimental world and the control
theoretic world is really a very good place to be, at least for me.
It sounds incredibly interesting.
I just want to comment on what you mentioned before about the constraints, if you want,
that biology imposes.
So maybe just to clarify the fact that all variables need to be positive, I guess that's
because we're always talking about concepts that are quantified quantities of things that
are out there, or I guess fluxes or other...
Concentrations.
Concentrations, exactly.
So it's incredible how positive system theory there has a huge role.
And the second thing that I wanted to mention is related to the question of realization
that you mentioned before.
I find it very fascinating that in this context, you're very much constrained, as you mentioned
by chemistry.
And so the realization theory, if you want, that you can build out of these systems has
to comply with those rules.
And I guess it imposes huge constraints because everything has to comply with the law of mass
action or with those nonlinear equations.
And therefore, it's very, very different from, again, the world, the realm of electricity.
But I also thought that maybe this is actually a good point, as you mentioned about the work
of your lab, to shift gears and to start talking about motifs.
And one of the motifs that your lab has developed, which I find incredibly interesting, as a
preview to the listeners, we're going to talk about one of the first PI controllers, if
not the first, I'm not sure about it, but I think it's the first, in biomolecular systems.
And this is something that gets me incredibly excited about the future of this branch of
control theory and systems and synthetic biology.
Yeah, so biologists like to talk about motifs.
That's not a word that exists, I guess, or is commonly used in our field in control
theory.
So let me just explain what a motif is.
So a motif is usually just a pattern that recurs with a frequency that is much higher
than one would expect if it were by chance.
So you could have a motif in terms of a sequence of nucleotides in a DNA that repeats.
What we're more interested in is network motifs.
And so these are simple network elements that implement a certain function that you
usually see much more frequently than chance, such that this small network forms a basis
for much more complex biological behavior.
So one example of that is a feedback loop.
So that would be a simple network motif, or a feedforward loop, or let's say an oscillator,
or a positive feedback loop.
So those are the different motifs.
When I first joined ETH in 2011, before actually joining, I was just doing purely systems biology,
so more analysis, system theory.
Now coming to ETH, I had the opportunity to start my own lab.
I have to say, before that, I hadn't touched a test tube in my life.
So it was a bit of an experience to kind of try to learn all of these techniques and build
a wet lab from scratch.
But I already had tenure.
I had nothing to lose.
And so if it didn't work, I would just close it.
That's the way you do it.
Continue doing theory as usual.
And that was one of the best decisions I had made, actually, professionally, is to start
a wet lab.
Initially, I thought I would just have one bench with one student, maybe doing some experiments
to verify the theory.
Right now, I have more than 16 different benches, and my group is actually more than half people
doing experiments.
So it's been a really very rewarding experience.
We didn't do it at the expense of theory.
We just sort of just added to the theoretical work and gave it much more color and life
and meaning.
And also to the theoretical questions that we ask are now very different, because they're
driven by what we see in the lab.
So having the ability to do experiments meant to me that now I can switch from doing system
theory to doing control theory.
So now we could do synthesis.
It didn't really make much sense to do synthesis if you're just doing analyzing existing systems.
Now, suppose you would like to design a new feature or you would like to control a living
cell in one way or another.
We started by using a technique that had been developed earlier called optogenetics, namely
developing cells that are actually sensitive to light so that you can actually control
them by shining light with different intensities.
That was the earlier problem.
So we would control, we would still use computer controllers, but the computer controllers
would send out signals that are light signals whose intensities actually serve as the actuation.
That was fun, and we actually were able to build the first feedback control system.
The computer controlled the gene expression at the time.
This was 2011.
But then another experience that I had in the past, namely integral feedback, came to
the front.
And the question was, can we build integral feedback controllers inside living cells?
You know, having shown that these systems naturally exist, for example, in calcium and
many other systems, it was obvious to ask the question, how would you build one?
Nobody had built integral feedback controllers.
And then, you know, we started trying to build a system that mimics the calcium homeostasis,
and we spent a lot of time on it, several years, two or three years, not really very
successfully.
One time, we thought we had it, and it was exhibiting zero steady state tracking errors,
everything that an integrator should do.
But to our disappointment, it was actually an artifact.
We discovered it was a biological artifact, and what we are seeing was not really the
action of an integral feedback controller.
It was a combination of negative feedback with disturbance feedforward that was behaving
very much like what an integrator would do.
And this went on for quite a while, and then I think the breakthrough came from the theory
side.
We had come up with a new motif that, which now we call, I called it the antithetic motif
for a reason that has to do with the way the molecules interact with each other.
So this antithetic motif, on paper, should be able to implement or realize integral feedback.
And it required two molecules, and you know, you can do negative variables by having two
positive variables and look at their difference, essentially.
And so this motif is a kind of a sequestration or annihilation motif, to use the term we
like to use in biology.
But essentially, two molecules bind with each other, and they prevent each other from being
active.
And one can use that behavior to realize integral feedback control systems.
And so the theory was nice.
And in fact, it turns out that these type of integral feedback controllers are also
noise resistant.
So they allow us to solve this problem with stochasticity or noise.
In fact, they would exploit noise so that they would function better in the presence
of noise.
Whereas if the system was noise-free, one would observe oscillations.
Now the presence of noise would actually lead to a dampening of this oscillation.
Very counterintuitive, but one can prove this mathematically.
And so then there was a sudden and abrupt switch in the lab.
Okay, drop everything that you're doing with these other systems.
Let's now try to implement these antithetic controllers.
It still took a good year and a half to two years to build them and verify that they were
functional.
But in fact, because we had to find the right biological molecules that had the behavior
that we were looking for, and it was a very stringent constraint.
You know, these molecules have to sequester each other.
Once they're bound, they could not function anymore to actuate.
And so we found them in the form of what's called sigma factors that exist already in
biology.
Once we built it, we could verify that we actually have an integral feedback controller
on our hands.
And I think these were very happy times because it really, from beginning to end, it took
a good part of seven years to build that first integral feedback controller.
But it was a glorious moment when this finally worked.
The paper appeared in Nature in 2019.
Now, to 2023, you know, we can build many of these, let's say one every two or three
months, with much better properties, better dynamic range.
It works in mammalian cells and bacterial cells.
So, you know, once we had that first integrator, we started learning about its property and
how to optimize it.
We have advanced quite a lot since then.
That must have felt like a real eureka moment, almost like in Harold Black developing the
negative feedback amplifier.
At least for me, it was, you know, the culmination of a lot of attempts, failed attempts and
a lot of effort.
For people in the lab, it was salvation because they no longer had to keep doing these experiments
that would take a long time.
You see, when you want to do, let's say, a simple time course, you know, and if you're
building a circuit, you know, you put a scope, a oscilloscope, and then you look at the voltage
up and you see whether steady state is achieved or not.
In biology, you know, steady state happens after 10 hours.
And so if you want to do a time course, then you have to do samples every so often during
this time course, and you have to do all sorts of dilution processes and freezing of these
samples and so on just to get one trace, only to find out that it hasn't worked for one
reason or another.
So it was a very grueling experience for people in the lab.
And when the new theory was developed, there was another small gift that came with this
theory, and that is that we could show that in the presence of noise, this motif is the
only motif that will implement integral feedback.
So this is kind of a necessary condition.
And the reason why this was good news for the experimentalists is just a realization
that this is the right motif.
We're not missing another motif that could have done this easier.
If it is to work, this is the only way it would work, right?
So this was completely reassuring, and it was just a matter of time when they got the
circuits to actually work the way we were expecting that they would work.
This is incredibly exciting, at least for me as a follower of this story.
It's fantastic.
I would like to dissect so many of the things that we touched on just in the last few minutes,
because we inadvertently touched on the enabling technologies that allowed this Eureka moment
to happen.
We also touched on the concept of antithetic integral feedback that I would like to dig
into a little bit more.
Yeah, maybe we can start from the former.
Initially, you were speaking about optogenetics, which, pun intended, allowed you to shed new
light on these biomolecular phenomena.
Maybe we can talk about the enabling technologies that allowed control theory to actually
implement these circuits.
Yeah, I think when I think of cybergenetics, at least the way I've thought about it, when
coming up with ways to do cellular control, one can think of two different flavors, right?
So general flavors.
One flavor, which is using computers to control living cells, so computers in the loop.
There, implementing any control system you like is easy and possible.
The challenge there is to interface the computer with the cell.
So what do you need for that?
Well, you need sensors and you need actuators.
In terms of the sensors, we would like to measure what the cell is doing.
Let's say how much gene is expressed.
I mean, this problem had been worked out.
There was a topic of a Nobel Prize 2008 in chemistry.
That's the well-known fluorescent protein, the discovery of the green fluorescent protein.
The main idea there is very simple.
If you have a protein that's being expressed by your gene, what you do is you genetically
engineer your gene such that, in addition to that protein, it fuses another protein
that fluoresces.
So when that original protein is expressed, attached to it is another fluorescent protein.
And by measuring the intensity of this fluorescence, you get an idea about the abundance of the
expressed protein.
And so that's one way to measure.
Initially, this was green fluorescent protein, but I think it wasn't long before other colors
where other wavelengths were developed.
And so one can look at multiple proteins simultaneously.
So you can do even multivariable control if you want.
But still very challenging with a single output.
So the idea, though, we can measure protein abundances.
So that solves the problem of sensing.
For that, you could either have your cells under a microscope, and then you would image
it, and you would, you know, see how much fluorescence that your cells have and quantify
that.
Or there's another device called a flow cytometer, which allows you to put a cell through a
microfluidic channel, shine a laser on it, see how much fluorescence.
So you can count the fluorescence of each individual cell, and you could do this for
hundreds of thousands of cells a minute.
So you can get a nice distribution for your population.
You can think of this as a snapshot of the probability density function of the expression.
So you can measure, you feed that to the computer, and then to actuate was a problem.
So how would we tell the cells how to express, how much to express based on what the computer
computes?
There, I think we found optogenetics.
And that was a technique that has been developed recently.
At the time, it was recent.
I guess now it's no longer recent.
So it allows cells to be light sensitive so that the more light you shine on the cell,
the more the gene is expressed.
OK, so this is an actuator.
We had since developed our own optogenetic systems in bacteria, in yeast, and in mammalian
cells that are particularly suited for control applications.
But at the time, we just used what was already out there, and it was sufficient.
Now you could do sensing, you could do actuation, and you can close the feedback loop with a
computer in the loop, and then you can control gene expression, which is something we managed
to do in 2011.
Since then, we've been using this technology to control cells in a bioreactor so that we
can optimize various protein products and various other applications.
So this is one flavor where the computer is in the loop.
The other flavor, which is actually in many ways is a bit harder, would be the controller
is in the cell, right?
So you have to genetically engineer the control system so that once you have a genetically
modified cell, when the genes, modified genes are expressed, they produce proteins that
interact with each other in a way that realizes your control system.
So this is what we had to do with the integral controller.
We had to modify genetically the cells, in that case it was E. coli at the time, so that
they express these sigma factors that aren't normally there in that particular bacterium.
It comes from another bacterium.
And such that when these proteins are expressed, they implement this antithetic motif and in
the process close the feedback loop.
So that's the genetically engineered controls.
And that's the second flavor of a feedback control.
Thanks for that.
You're doing an excellent job in clarifying, at least to me, how should I just visualize
even systems that you're acting on?
So I guess in my imagination, at least, I'm visualizing a microscope endowed with some
tool that allows you to shine light onto.
We have our cells in little containers that shine light through them.
And in that particular case, we had to develop new technology to allow us to shine light
on individual cells.
And that's kind of, again, using MEMS technology, microelectromechanical systems.
So technology that was developed for projectors.
And these are called digital micromirror devices.
So these are, you can think about it as an array of millions of micromirrors, each of
which can be controlled with an electrostatic field.
And in this way, you can point the mirrors any direction you want.
So you can shine light on a single cell or on even a subcellular compartment with the
intensity that you want.
So this allows us to very, very precisely target individual cells.
And we can have a controller for that one cell.
You cannot see it with your naked eye, but there's a controller in the computer running
in feedback for that particular cell.
And you can do this simultaneously and in parallel for thousands of cells.
And so that's, again, brings in technology to allow us to do the feedback control of
individual cells.
I was about to mention that.
So there is an immense challenge also from a technological perspective in order to implement
actuators, as you say, and sensors, which seems to be something easy as we, at least
you make it sound like it's something easy, but it's definitely not.
It's a huge component of your work, I guess.
But I also found very interesting what you mentioned about controllers that are acting
in living cells.
And I was wondering, what do you use as media to create those controllers?
Should I imagine viruses acting into a cell or how does it work?
So how do we introduce our controllers?
Exactly.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, there are different ways.
So in the lab, what we normally do is we use electroporation.
So a process by which you subject the cells to an electric field and their membranes become
moreallows you to introduce genetic material inside the cell.
So this is by far the most common way, electroporation.
And that works reasonably well.
So it allows you to introduce new genetic material inside the cell.
In a lot of the treatments that people do, if you want to access, let's say, cells in a
living human or in a mouse model, there are different vehicles.
So one can think of using viruses, lentiviruses, as a vehicle for delivering genetic material.
And viruses have evolved to be very efficient and effective at penetrating host cells and
to deliver their own DNA to infect the cell.
So now people can or biologists can exploit that feature.
And instead of having the native DNA of the virus, they introduce their own, let's say,
therapeutic genetic material into that virus that then goes on to deliver the material.
So these are some of the tricks by which you would introduce novel genetic material that
then gets expressed into your favorite circuit, synthetic circuit.
That's incredible.
Again, it sounds like science fiction, but it's incredible that we're actually able to
do such things.
I'd like to take a step back before we move on towards something that I find incredibly
exciting.
So the applications of all these ideas.
What can we hope to achieve with these tools?
Spending the last few words maybe on the antithetic integral feedback motif.
First of all, I'd like to understand the reason of calling it antithetic integral feedback.
And then I'd like to understand how it works a little bit from a control theoretic perspective.
Okay.
Without equations.
I understand it's a huge challenge, but we can try.
Yeah.
Okay.
So why it's called antithetic?
Well, that goes back to the way this works.
So at the basis of this antithetic controller are two controller molecules.
We call them Z1 and Z2.
One molecule, Z1, gets expressed at a constant rate.
Okay.
And it's stable, so it doesn't degrade.
So you're just producing this molecule at a constant rate.
The other molecule, Z2, acts like a sensor.
And so the rate of production depends on the abundance of the molecule you want to regulate.
Okay.
So the rate of synthesis of Z2 is proportional to the variable, let's say, x, that you want
to keep constant.
And now the reaction, the key reaction underlying this motif is a reaction in which one molecule
of Z1 binds to another molecule of Z2, and they mutually annihilate each other.
Strictly speaking, they don't have to annihilate each other.
They could still be bound as long as the complex is not functional, things will still work.
But let's just say they annihilate each other.
Okay.
One to one.
So this process is, I mean, so the two molecules are in some ways antagonistic to each other.
That's the name, antithetic control.
In fact, when I called it that, I didn't have any idea that actually many of the motifs
we will find out later on to implement this are things like sigma factor anti-sigma.
They were already called like this, you know, sigma anti-sigma, toxin anti-toxin, you know,
holon anti-holon.
These are all pairs of molecules that have exactly the property we want for realizing
this motif.
And so it was appropriate to use that antithetic terminology, it was fortunate that we used
it at the time.
So how does this work?
Yeah, that's, so if you think about this operation, Z1 and Z2, and, you know, they have this
property that they bind with each other.
If you have an abundance of Z1 and abundance of Z2, and let's say they bind together one
to one, then what's left is the difference, right, between Z1 or Z2, if it's positive
or not.
So this allows you to do this positive negative type of thing.
And the integration happens because of the nature of the operation.
These things are being produced at a dynamic rate.
And so when you subtract the dynamics of production of Z1 and Z2, what you're left with is the
difference between them.
The dynamics of the difference is what actually implements the integral of the error.
So the difference of two positive quantities can be positive or negative.
So this allows us to also overcome this issue with the sign.
I mean, that's roughly speaking.
And I can show you in the right, you know, in 30 seconds if I write the equation.
Now, of course, there will be a link in the description to everything that we talked about.
So of course, the Nature paper from 2019, but also a wonderful, I would call it an overview
or almost a manifesto paper about cybergenetics that appeared on the proceedings of the IEEE
in 2022.
I just wanted to clarify for terminology for the audience of control theory.
What does it mean actually to annihilate?
And what does it mean to bind?
I know that these are very naive questions, but it might be worth just mentioning what
those mean.
Yeah, I guess I should have explained those things because I myself had struggled with
these concepts when I was first learning.
So binding is the process in which two molecules combine and form a complex.
So A plus B gives you C. C consists of both A and B, so this is a binding event.
And now the bound species may have different properties, right?
It could be inactive, whereas A and B are on their own active.
When they bind together, they could annihilate.
So they could inactivate each other.
Annihilation just simply means that they mutually degrade each other, right?
So that the protein is no longer functional.
Maybe it's ideally it gets broken down into amino acids that get recycled.
Very often that's not what actually happens.
You don't really need it to be annihilated.
It's just an idealization.
All they need to do is just deactivate.
They just need to be non-functional in the complex form.
Should I picture it as the concentration exponentially decreases of this substance
or what do you mean by it's no longer functional?
Like, let's say, for example, Z1.
Z1, in order to close the feedback loop, has to activate another gene that closes the feedback
loop.
Now, when it's bound to Z2, it can no longer do that.
So it no longer acts as an activator.
It's inert, if you wish, biologically inert.
Whereas before the binding event, Z1 is a functional molecule that's a variable that
activates other variables and closes the feedback loop.
Now, once it's in that complex form, it's out of the picture.
You can just completely ignore it in terms of the chemical reactions.
It's no longer functional.
So while we're on this subject, I also want to touch on two other things that I believe
are incredibly exciting.
So one of them is that, of course, after 2019, you moved forward and you added derivative
action as well.
I mean, proportional and derivative action.
So at the moment, we do have a real PID controller for biomolecular systems.
Am I right?
Not quite.
So we have since built PI controllers and demonstrated them in mammalian cells, which
is always important because the way we want to use them for medical applications.
We've also come up with all the right motifs that one would need to implement the derivative
aspect of part of the controller.
But we haven't to date demonstrated a PID.
We have demonstrated a PI, but we're working on the last bit, the D.
Admittedly, it's less important than the PI does most of the work that you need.
So it's just, I think, it would be nice and satisfying to have the derivative component.
This is another question.
How would you implement different derivatives using biological component?
I mean, it turns out if you know how to build an integrator and you put an integrator in
a feedback loop with a unity feedforward path, then so if you have an identity for
the forward loop and then an integrator in the feedback loop, what you end up with in
the transfer function between the input and the output is actually a differentiator with
a low-pass filter, which is exactly what we need.
We need the low-pass filter as well.
As you know, all differentiators have low-pass filters in practice.
And so having implemented an integrator, we have the ingredient that's needed to
implement a differentiator.
It's not the only way, but it's actually one way to do it.
And it's just, I think, a matter of time when this finally works.
I think for applications, as I mentioned, it may not be necessary.
There are reasons why you want to have a differentiator, similar to the reasons why
control engineers in the field use PID and not just PI.
You know, you can get faster response and good transients and so on.
It could also reduce variability, so cell-to-cell variability.
But strictly speaking, it's not necessary.
In fact, you know, working in the field with a company when I was back in the U.S., I noticed
that very often the engineers have PID controllers, but they actually have turned off the D part.
They just use it as a PI.
I guess 95% of the real PIDs actually do work like that.
Yeah.
I find very, very interesting the fact that, you know, the conceptual analogies that you
do make with transfer functions actually work in practice.
So one is guided by those concepts to realize something that is physically very, very different
to the ideas that we have in mind.
I also thought that before, you know, moving towards the applications and the future of
this field, it would be interesting to talk about the actual systems that you do work on.
You mentioned that mammalian cells are something that is important for demonstrative purposes,
but generally that's not the only type of cell that you do work on, right?
Yeah, that's correct.
I mean, normally in this business, there are a few organisms that serve as model organisms
where, you know, the genetics have been worked out.
There's a lot of tools that people have used.
And so, you know, people tend to work with those model organisms or model cells because
life is much easier that way.
I mean, biology is already hard enough.
Why make it even more complicated by working on some exotic bacterium that, you know, perhaps
the genetics of which haven't been worked out yet.
And so some of these model organisms are things like E. coli, right?
So E. coli is probably the best understood living organism, more than us.
Yeast, budding yeast, so the baker's yeast is another model organism that kind of has
a nucleus, unlike the bacteria that doesn't have a nucleus.
So it's called the eukaryotic cell because of that.
And of course, us, you know, that's mammalian cells, right?
So the sizes of these cells differs drastically.
So with the E. coli being the tiniest, and then the yeast in between, and the mammalian
cells are huge in comparison.
But also the genetic challenges are also different.
So mammalian cells are more complicated to work with.
They take more time.
Reagents are much more expensive.
But of course, they're much more important, right, for us.
So if you're thinking about therapeutics, even if you want to do things like antibody
production in a bioreactor, you still need to work with Joe cells, and those are mammalian
cells.
So the evolution of my lab started from E. coli.
It was the simplest organism.
It was the easiest to do genetic tests.
It was the fastest and the cheapest.
And then as we gained more confidence, we felt that if we are to have an impact on biomedical
applications, we had better tackle the mammalian cells.
And so gradually, we added yeast cells and as well as mammalian cells.
And now I think most people in my group work on mammalian synthetic biology, with all the
challenges and also the opportunities that come with that.
So and what type of mammalian cells, if I may ask?
So there are different types we work with.
We work on cells called HeLa cells.
These are one type of cells.
Another type we work on are called HeK cells.
And then we also work on stem cells, so mouse embryonic stem cells.
So those are the three cell types that we mostly work with.
And I think we will start soon working on Joe cells.
So these are hamster cells, hamsteric cells.
Okay.
Yeah.
So maybe now it's a good moment to shift gears and move towards the future.
So the applications of this field that you dubbed cybergenetics, what can we actually
achieve?
I mean, I know that there are things nowadays that are science fiction, almost.
We were chatting yesterday, just before recording this episode, that we can nowadays control
the firing, individual firing in nerve cells of mice or rats, I forget.
So the ability to engineer living cells opens up quite a bit of possibilities.
Yes, that's right.
I mean, one can think of it in different ways.
I mean, you can think of agriculture.
Of course, genetic engineering methods are well known in agriculture, but also industrial
biotechnology.
So this is one area that I'm also excited about.
You would like to be able to make a new protein, maybe more effectively or cheaply, and you
would like to do it in such a way that you can control the different enzymes and the
rate of flux at different pathways so that you can get just the optimal amount of protein
expression.
Now, with cybergenetic techniques using light, we can do this.
We have recently demonstrated that we can produce more, have higher yields by simply
closing the feedback loop.
And in this case, one can measure, for example, the amount of stress a cell has through this
fluorescent protein technology that I told you about, and use that information to decide
how much expression a particular gene should have, right?
So if you have a gene that produces a product of interest, a protein of interest, overexpressing
it is not the best way to get more yield because then the cells get stressed and actually
your yield goes down.
And if you underexpress, again, you're not exploiting the maximum capacity of your cell
to produce that protein.
There's a sweet spot somewhere in between, and to try to find out where that sweet spot
is and to regulate gene expression, because this sweet spot is moving, you regulate the
gene expression so you're always tracking that sweet spot.
This, I think, is one huge opportunity for cybergenetics in industrial biotechnology.
Very often, the impediment is that you have intermediates that are toxic.
And so by knowing what the levels of these intermediates are and adjusting variables
like gene expression, you can keep the toxicity level to the bare minimum and in the process
enhance the yield.
So we have in my lab bioreactors or photobioreactors.
So these are bioreactors that we have outfitted with LEDs, and we shine the light in feedback
to control the entire population.
We're not doing single cell control, but we are looking at whole population level control.
The other application I'm really excited about for synthetic biology is the therapeutic
applications, the medical implications.
And that's more long term and more challenging.
It takes longer time and also has lots of challenges.
I mean, you want to haveanytime you put in a modified cell in a human, you need to
get FDA approval.
It's a complex and long process, but it's also extremely promising.
So one example of this isso in, I think, 2017 or 2018, FDA approved the use of CAR-T
cells for immunotherapy.
And this has been one of the most successful treatments for cancer, right?
So immunotherapy.
So these are cells that are genetically modified to attack cancer cells, and essentially it
allows immune response, immune system to target cancer cells.
And these cells originate from the patient or from a donor.
They're modified in the lab and then put back into the patient's blood so that they
can treat diseases.
So the problem is that all of these systems, these cell therapies, generally work in an
open loop.
And so the idea is to actually bring in some of these controllers that we've been developing
and have these cells work in a closed loop fashion so that they're sensing the disease
state and then producing the amount of therapy, therapeutic, just the right amount to regulate
the level of, let's say, a particular biomarker, disease biomarker.
And so that's the goal that we have in the lab, and that's what we're working towards.
We're making better and better PID controllers or PI controllers, and then adding safety
features to them so that they can become, let's say, medical grade so that they have
anti-wind-up schemes and, you know, the usual things one has to worry about when implementing
integrators in the feedback loop.
But really, if you really think about it, most of diseases are essentially due to or
can be attributed to feedback loops that have gone awry, right?
So, you know, think about cancer, think about diabetes, and so on.
Many of the diseases we encounter are essentially due to the
Genetic circuits going astray.
Yeah, genetic circuits for various reasons, right?
And so, by having the technology to replace these with genetically engineered cells that
function as robust control systems, I think we would be able to contribute to disease.
At least that's the guiding principle for us and for what we do.
And, you know, we will see what happens.
This is a long process.
It's not something that you can do in the lab today and test it on people the next day.
There has to be some different trials, clinical trials, different phases,
and it takes years and years.
But we have to start somewhere.
This is so, so cool.
It is science fiction, and I think it's fantastic to watch, you know, from an external perspective.
I kind of envision these things as almost like we are building genetic robots, which is
incredible.
And I guess it also comes with very important ethical challenges.
Is this something that you thought about?
Yes, I think ethics comes with synthetic biology from day one, right?
Anytime you want to modify something genetically, I think one has to think about the consequences.
What we do in the lab, you know, these bacteria, they don't survive outside the lab.
So whatever modifications we have will have no consequences.
However, these days, the tools are available to do much more powerful genetic changes.
For example, CRISPR-Cas.
I think that this is a new technology that led to a Nobel Prize that allows scientists to
modify DNA with precision and efficiency.
And this led to a lot of discussions about what one should be able to change or not to change.
I mean, the danger, of course, is that you can have these CRISPR babies, as they're called.
And there has been already some gross violations by one of the scientists who modified human
cells to have, you know, two new babies that have modified DNA.
And I think that's very dangerous grounds.
There's a fundamental difference between changing, let's say, regular cells and changing,
for example, skin cells or liver cells or cancer cells in one patient,
and changing cells that propagate, like, for example, sperm cells or egg cells,
because the genetic modifications are not restricted to the individual,
but they are passed on to their progeny.
And that's much, much more dangerous.
And I think this is something that we are not ready right now to,
or scientists are not ready to go down that path.
There are certain other diseases where actually you could do a lot of good by modifying the DNA.
Let's say, for example, some patients that have genes that have various mutations that
lead to diseases.
And so if you can imagine modifying these genes through gene therapy, for example,
and reversing or correcting these mutations to restore normal functions,
I think that's a very exciting area of gene therapy.
But whatever modifications are made are not passed on to the progeny.
So I think this is a safer way of doing genetic engineering.
They're clearly dangerous, right?
So one has to watch out not to make modifications to a cell or, let's say, a bacterium that then
becomes more lethal and escapes the lab and so on.
And so we have to put in place various measures to ensure that this never happens.
And I think ethics goes hand in hand with this business of synthetic biology.
Like many other technologies, I think one has to be careful to put in place the right
measures to make sure that the chances of accidents like that are basically zero.
So with a lot of these, let's say, cell therapies, one hears about what's so-called kill switches.
So if you put in the wrong therapy or something happens to the patient that has
these genetically engineered cells, there would be the opportunity to kill the cell.
So this would be additional circuitry added on top of the genetic circuit to stop everything.
And so these are some of the measures people look at for trying to mitigate some of these
risks.
But at the same time, I mean, if you have a patient that is dying and they have
exhausted all other possibilities and there's a new cell therapy available that could give
them the chance to live longer or overcome the disease, I think then one has to take
that into account as well in making these calculations.
Yeah, I guess it's very much context dependent.
One thing I wanted to talk about, and then maybe we can move on towards the end of this
episode, was a paper that I read from you recently.
It's about the internal model principle.
I know it has little to do with the applications, but it's something that is very close to my
heart, something that I really, really like from classical control theory.
And I thought it would be nice to touch on that as well before closing.
Yeah, thanks for bringing this up.
This is something I've been very excited about recently.
So this is a paper, I guess the PNAS paper that you're referring to, appeared two or
three months ago.
So what this work addresses, and this is, again, I was talking about having to develop
a new control theory that's particularly suited for biology, and this is a perfect
example of that.
I guess as control people, we are taught early on at the graduate level what the internal
model principle of Francis and Wanam and, you know, the necessity of certain type of
structures, integral feedback, and so on for tracking and rejecting various types of disturbances.
These systems, though, that were addressed by this work are mostly linear systems, and
they are not positive variables.
They are not constrained by chemical reaction constraints.
And so in biology, the game is a little bit different.
Now, so for this particular work, we started by defining something called robust perfect
adaptation.
This was available for the literature.
We were not the first to introduce it, but it's a useful notion.
Essentially, it means tracking and disturbance rejection at the steady state that is robust,
right?
So robust to what?
Robust to parameter changes, robust to topological changes in the network.
And we know, for example, in the case of constant in time disturbances and signals, that integral
feedback is sufficient for such a robustness, and it's necessary for linear systems.
So how would one address this question if the underlying system is a bunch of molecules
interacting with each other through chemical reactions?
So they're positive variables.
And what we were looking at is how do you define robustness in this case?
And we looked at the particularly strong notion of robustness.
We called it maximal robust perfect adaptation.
In other words, the system has to be robust to changes in all the variables, all the parameters,
all the reaction rates, except for the ones that determine the set point, like the dial
that tunes in what the reference should be, right?
You can't be robust to that.
Shouldn't be, even.
So that's the maximal robust perfect adaptation.
That's what it means.
So what kind of biological networks allow you to do perfect tracking that is robust
to these kind of perturbations?
And we managed to obtain an answer.
And the answer is different depending on whether this network is deterministic or it has noise.
So it's a stochastic network, with the stochastic network's controllers being more stringent.
So all of the controllers that work for the stochastic network will work for the deterministic,
but not the other way around.
There are motifs that will work for the noise-free case, that will not work, will break down
in the noisy case.
For the noisy case, interestingly, we found that underlying all such motifs,
there is the antithetic motif at the heart as the main core component.
But more importantly, so we have an algebraic test, a very simple algebraic test.
You give me the network.
I can apply, look at the certain matrix, and look at those properties.
And then from there, I can tell you whether this network has this adaptation property or not.
And so that's one of the benefits.
And if it does have this property, if it does adapt, I can construct the integrator,
which is usually not obvious.
Very often, it's a way or a combination of molecules that interact with each other
in a certain way to implement this integral feedback.
And so this theory allows you to actually find the integrator,
which you wouldn't be able to do otherwise.
So that's why I think this is kind of nice from a control theoretic point of view.
It links in classical notions of internal model principles from Murray and Wanham
with sort of modern day biochemical reaction network theory.
And we have a nice clean answer.
There's still a lot of open problems, but at least for this particular formulation
that I just described to you, the answer is clean and it's complete.
Oddly enough, I found that this revival of the, let's say,
an interest on the internal model principle has appeared in many different branches of
control theory.
I've seen papers coming from the neuroscience aspects.
Of course, many people in the motor control area are also very interested in this concept.
And as a groupie, if you want, of this concept myself, I find it very exciting.
I think now is really the time to close this episode.
It's going to be probably very long.
So apologies to the audience, but it was, I hope, very interesting.
It was definitely very interesting to me.
And as I mentioned also to many other guests of the podcast,
I like to ask the question of advice to future students.
So people that are interfacing with the idea of continuing in this field
or potentially venturing into the synthetic biology or cyber genetics field,
what is your best advice?
Okay, interesting.
So I'm going to give probably a non-traditional advice,
but it's one I actually do believe in.
And one that I was inspired by a quote from Richard Hamming.
I don't know if you know Richard Hamming or not, of course,
if you had an electrical engineering background.
A stroke of genius.
Yeah.
And he had the Hamming filter.
He had also Hamming windows and Hamming codes and so on.
And he worked with Bell Labs.
So Richard Hamming was interested in the creative process
and how people do research.
And he actually wrote several articles on this.
And one thing that specifically struck me is the following quote.
Let's see if I can remember it.
And he says something like this.
He says,
Most scientists spend almost all of their time
working on problems that even they don't consider great,
nor do they consider these problems will lead to great work.
And so he says,
Then if you are working on unimportant problems,
you're not going to end up with important work,
except by the dumbest of luck.
So this may seem trivial,
maybe obvious that, of course,
if you don't work on important problems,
you don't end up doing important work.
But I think considering that many people
know that the problems they're working on are not important,
and I think it behooves us to give this more thought.
So if you are starting,
if you're a new student that are starting to look for a PhD problem,
then I think it is useful to always ask yourself,
even though the problem that you're working on seems interesting,
and the solution approach is interesting,
and the tools are interesting,
how relevant would be the solution?
If you are to solve what you're trying to solve,
what would be the impact?
And if it's minimal,
maybe it's a chance to look for another problem that has a more impact.
And I think really few people think about this.
Usually the way you end up working on certain problems by chance,
you talk to somebody, or you hear a talk,
and you say,
Ah, that sounds interesting.
I can use this tool or that tool.
And you get involved with the problem details,
and it's fun and exciting.
But at the end of the day,
is it relevant?
Is it important?
And I think it's a good idea to ask oneself every now and then,
Am I working on important problems?
There are always exciting tools and exciting approaches,
no matter what field you work on.
So I think simply by addressing this question head on early,
I think one could, let's say,
have a better chance of having an impact once a solution is obtained.
So that's my advice is, you know,
ask yourself, is this an important problem?
Because if it's not an important problem,
it's not likely to lead to important results.
I'm not saying it will for sure not lead to important,
which sometimes, you know, there is,
you might run into something that ends up being important.
You didn't intend to solve that problem,
but you know, it's just serendipity kicks in, right?
Still, I think to the extent that you have an impact on what problems you choose,
I think it's a good idea to think about the potential impact of a solution.
Well, Mustafa, with this, I think we can close this episode.
Thank you so much for joining us on the show.
Thank you very much, Alberto.
It's great to be here on your program.
Follow us on Spotify, support on Patreon or PayPal,
and connect with us on social media platforms.
See you next time.