Hello and welcome to In Control, the first podcast on control theory.
Here we discuss the science of feedback, decision making, artificial intelligence and much more.
I'm your host Alberto Padoan, live from a recording studio in Zurich.
Big thanks to our sponsor, the National Centre of Competence in Research on Dependable Ubiquitous
Automation, as well as the International Federation of Automatic Control.
Our guest today is Rodolf Sapulka, from the University of Cambridge, is Professor of Engineering
in the Control Group.
Welcome to the show, Rodolf.
Thank you.
And good morning, Alberto.
So I should probably give a small disclaimer that I've been spending a lot of time with
Rodolf over three years in Cambridge.
Some time ago in my past, it's been a pleasure to do so and so it will be potentially a semi
different episode in the sense that I know you better than other people.
And so having spent quite some time together, I know you are an avid reader and an avid
hiker.
So I guess just to break the ice, I'm curious about knowing what is on your reading list
at the moment.
Wow.
A very unexpected question.
There are always many things on the reading list.
But actually, there is nothing on the reading list right at the minute, strangely enough.
And often the best novels that I've read, I discovered them by complete accident, for
instance, in the bookstore of an airport.
And so I'm always, I like to be surprised.
And sometimes this leads to the best reads.
I'm curious.
So, OK, one quote, one from one of your favorite readers is Oran Pamuk, a Nobel Prize in Literature
in 2006.
So he said in The New Life, I read a book one day and my whole life was changed.
So if that were to be the book, which one would it be for you?
Which book?
Yes.
That changed my life.
Yeah.
I don't think I could single out one book also because books, yeah, maybe it will be
a strange answer to your question.
But as a teenager, I was totally fascinated by Dostoyevsky.
And then there was a strange event that occurred to me when I was around 40.
And one day I picked a book of Dostoyevsky and I said, let's go back to it.
And I stopped after three pages.
And I realized at that time that the emotion that you can experience while reading a book
is extremely dependent on your age, your environment, your stage in life.
And so I think that it's not that certain books are objectively monuments.
Of course they are.
But I think it's always a story of resonance.
And so it's a resonance at a particular time for a special reason between the reader and
the writer.
That's how I would describe my experience with books.
I actually love this answer because it kind of adds a dynamic element to a book.
It's not something that is there forever, but it really has to be a synergy between
the reader and the book itself.
It's always an encounter.
Yes.
Very fascinating.
So since you mentioned you being a teenager, I like to always draw a sort of picture of
your trajectory as a human.
Yeah.
So I'm curious about what brought you to control.
So like, what is it about, say, your environment or your childhood or anything that you can
think of that brought you to control?
That's very hard to answer.
Again, I don't have a very clear answer.
I can pinpoint events that eventually brought me where I am.
And so one event that perhaps I could tell about what led me to control, even though
it has nothing to do with control, is that it was my second year of engineering.
And it was the course of thermodynamics, which was definitely not my favorite subject at
the time.
But I remember very vividly that the professor once entered the classroom and was nearly
shooting at us and saying, have you heard of what has just been reported that for the
first time ever, one has observed superconductivity above 30 degrees Kelvin.
And that experiments will change the world.
And he went on and for the best part of the lecture, he just told us about these experiments
and why it was fascinating and what would be the consequence of it.
And I don't remember anything of what he told, but I do remember his eyes.
And I do remember the light and I would say the fire during that lecture.
And perhaps it is the moment in my life where I sort of experienced for the first time that
there is such an intimate connection between teaching and research.
And I would say that today I would pinpoint that event as something that led me to my
profession, even though I'm sure that at the time, you know, it was just a complete accident.
Perhaps this professor doesn't remember that he told those stories.
Again, it is a sort of a resonance that is completely accidental.
And I think of any trajectory as somehow interpolating between those events.
And those events are always independent of you.
They are very accidental.
So you could wonder whether how an identity can be defined by such stochastic events.
But at the same time, I like to think that where I am today is not that dependent on
those events and that perhaps a completely different sequence of events would have led
to a trajectory that would not be so different.
And to me, this is a mystery of life.
The fact that we are so much determined by accidental events.
And at the same time, our own identity is not so much in these events, but how we respond
to those events.
And maybe this is my fascination for control theory, because after all, control theory
is a science where you study the interaction between the external and the internal.
We study how systems respond to disturbances.
I find this quite deep and central to engineering, actually.
And decision making is the only lever that you can pull somehow.
I mean, it's definitely fascinating.
I guess the only comment I have is that in a sense, one cannot repeat the experiment
as to the best of our knowledge.
Absolutely.
So we don't know who we would be with another sequence of events.
But this is not something that causes me any anxiety, I would say.
It's also a fact that all these events that I sort of would pinpoint today to define my
trajectory always involve human beings and always involve encounters, those resonance
that I was talking about earlier.
I cannot remember reading a book or reading a text and saying, this is going to change
my life.
But I can pinpoint a sentence that someone told me and that somehow became very important
in my life.
Yeah.
That changed the course of events in a sense.
Well, I mean, I guess one of the things that I really want to mention is that, you know,
by interacting with you over the years, one of the things I learned from you is an appreciation
for the history of a problem.
And so I found a very nice quote from Kepler from the Astronomia Nova.
So he says, the roads by which men arrive at their insights into celestial matters seem
to me almost as worthy of wonder as those matters themselves.
So today I would like to try and draw, you know, your trajectory.
You started from at least academically speaking from a paper with your PhD advisor, stability
for dynamical systems with first integrals, a topological criteria.
So something very mathematical and very much rooted in nonlinear control.
And today I would say that your manifesto that we will talk about certainly in a second
is towards building spiking control systems.
So how do we connect these two points?
What happened in the middle?
Yeah, again, it's a very strange sequence of events and the events don't really explain
the outcome.
But I think that control theory requires a lot of mathematical abstraction.
And at the same time, I think that control theory to me is really engineering driven.
So the important contributions of control have always come from very concrete engineering
questions.
And it is this meeting point between the abstraction and the concreteness of the questions that
attracts me and that I think has always attracted me in control.
So my engineering education was quite mathematical.
In fact, my specialty was mathematical engineering, if such a thing exists.
So definitely I had a taste for mathematics, as I think many people in control have.
But over the years, I became more and more sympathetic to the concreteness of control.
And this is also what I like about the basic control courses, is that it's hard, I think,
to pinpoint other courses early in the curriculum, where there is such a bridge made between,
you know, the very concrete questions of making the speed of a motor insensitive to
load and complex analysis.
How comes that those things connect to each other?
How comes that a little bit of abstraction is so powerful in providing such concrete
answer that I find fascinating in control?
I totally agree.
And probably I wouldn't even have started this podcast if I weren't so fascinated.
I guess here we are almost at a crossing point in the sense that we can either follow
the chronological course of events and, you know, follow your trajectory starting from
deep theoretical questions in nonlinear control or start in a bit of an unusual way right
from the present.
So what keeps you busy these days?
And I would probably ask you, actually, what do you prefer?
I have no preference.
Of course, it's always easier to speak about the presence.
That's what, you know, keeps me awake.
So let's speak about the present.
I think the present is a very exciting thing to talk about.
At least I was reading the other day your paper on the IEEE proceedings, Spiking Control
Systems, to me that is really a manifesto almost towards what are you going to do over
the probably the next decade, I believe.
I really liked one quote where you say explicitly, we aim at developing a control theory of spiking
systems which will apply both to the natural world of biophysical neural circuits and the
post digital technology of event based systems.
I think that sentence is a masterpiece.
And it somehow is transparent that you also want to inherit all the heritage from cybernetics.
But moving forward, you want to incorporate new knowledge, let's say, coming from control
systems and the mixed feedback principle that we will definitely talk about in a second.
So what is your goal and your motivation, I would say, as well?
Yeah, my motivation is very clearly to focus on the importance of event based systems and
event based control.
As a topic that has received, I would consider very, very little attention in control.
The name I think was quote uncoined by Karl Astrum and his book chapter of 2007 that is
called event based control.
My reading of that book chapter is that itself it builds upon a paper that Karl Astrum wrote
in 1991, together with Carl Vermeet, the father of neuromorphic engineering.
And that brings the importance of events.
And it's very, very defeating to talk about events and to do research about events nowadays,
because our language and the language of information engineering has become so divided between
the analog language on the one hand and digital language on the other hand.
And events are clearly something that mixed the continuous and the digital.
And as a control theorist, I've come to regard this story as a story of mixed feedback, the
positive feedback being associated to discrete states and by stability and automata and the
language of digital technology, and negative feedback being associated with homeostasis,
regulation, and the theory of continuous regulation.
It is only through time and because I was studying neuroscience and because I started
reading what I was seeing in neuroscience as a theory of mixed feedback that I became
aware that in fact cybernetics was a science of mixed feedback.
And I think many people in the community would agree that the cybernetics age was a sort
of a golden age, very short lived golden age of control.
And that nowadays there are many signs that we are sort of returning to that age.
But much better equipped, because in the meantime, we have developed fantastic tools
that we can now use to reconsider questions that perhaps were ahead of their time.
But definitely my view is that the digital age created this strong separation between
positive feedback and negative feedback and that control theory became a theory of negative
feedback and that it is a little bit today the trap where control theory or the corner
where control theory is sitting, and that there is so much more to explore and to be
connected both to biology, but also to now these fast developing event-based sensors
and event-based actuators that is opening so many new questions and new path of research
for control theories that I find is very, very exciting.
There's a lot to unpack in what you just said.
I just want to maybe mention a couple of things for our audience.
And then I guess we will delve into some of the concepts that you mentioned so far.
So first of all, I just want to mention to the audience of control theory, let's say
that who Carver Mead is.
Carver Mead worked with John Hopfield and Richard Feynman, novelist, helping to create
three new fields, neural networks, neuromorphic engineering, and the physics of computation.
Just to name a few, he founded at least 20 companies from integrated circuits to silicon
sensors for photographic imaging.
So he was really a pioneering figure in the history of science.
But since you were mentioning, first of all, the notion of mixed feedback or the mixed
feedback principle, maybe we should try to unpack that.
So what does that imply or how can we explain, let's say, to our audience, what is the mixed
feedback principle?
So the mixed feedback terminology comes from the mixed feedback amplifier that features
the cover of the well-known textbooks of electrical circuits by Desueur and Shua from the 80s.
And on the cover of the textbooks, you see the op-amp with a wire both connected to the
negative part of the, so a feedback wire, a wire connecting the output of the amplifier
both to the negative part of the amplifier and to the positive part of the amplifier.
And the story of the feedback amplifier that we know in control theory, that I knew in
control theory, was the story of negative feedback.
Historically, things went the other way around.
The first use of the op-amp was the positive feedback amplifier, because that was the way
to design switches in analog systems.
And so until the Second World War, the only way to realize switching circuits and circuits
that were not equilibrium circuits was through positive feedback amplifiers.
And this makes the discovery of Black, of the negative feedback amplifier, only more
impressive that he had this vision that there could be a use of connecting the output of
the op-amp to the negative part, because that would make the op-amp less sensitive to
disturbance, less sensitive to uncertainty.
And so we know that it took, I think, nine years for Black to get his discovery patented.
And so that shows the spirit of the time, that why would you ever connect the output
of a system to the negative part?
And today we have just the opposite view, at least as a student.
And I remember speaking to some control theorists and talking to them about positive feedback
and seeing that face, that why would you ever connect the output of an op-amp to the positive part?
And then the way I read any device in the body, and in particular in the brain, is a
mixed feedback amplifier.
And so nature somehow is making use of this mixed feedback amplification all the time.
And I think for very good reasons.
So yeah, this is my short story of the mixed feedback concept.
Maybe like just to help the audience grasp what it really means.
So I guess what you're advocating is that in a feedback loop, there's always, if we're
interested, let's say, in building systems that range, let's say, from the analog behavior
to the digital behavior, we should mix, really have elements that both have positive feedback
and negative feedback in order to be able to capture, let's say, almost all behaviors
of interest.
Is that fair to say?
But at least in my view, to sort of reunite the two branches of control that are automation
and regulation.
So today, you know, the conferences are different, the classes are different, the textbooks are
different, and you choose your side.
Either you study automation through automata to the language of discrete states, finite
state machines, or you study continuous control systems, and the world of regulation and the
world of which is fundamentally an analog world.
And I think that the best of those two worlds comes together when you consider mixed feedback.
Something that was sort of, I think, very well appreciated in the 40s, the time where
of the golden age of the mixed feedback amplifier, but then somehow disappeared from the field.
I guess this is a good point where to mention how does the mixed feedback principle enter
into the picture of neuroscience?
So I guess we could mention some of the paradigmatic models of how a single neuron behaves.
That's probably a good example.
Well, of course, the fundamental model of neuronal excitability that goes back to Hodgkin
and Huxley in 1952, is precisely the model of explaining the action potential of a neuron,
so the spike, as through the analogy of an electrical circuit, where you attach to an
RC circuit, so a passive circuit, you attach two current sources, one providing positive
feedback and the other one providing negative feedback.
And identifying those two current sources was the fundamental insight of Hodgkin and
Huxley and is the mechanism of thresholds.
And so what we, I think, the fundamental elements that we now see appearing in technology is
the value of thresholds.
And so as long as you use negative feedback, as long as you only consider negative feedback
control, you are in the world of equilibrium systems, so you always reject disturbance
and try to go back to equilibrium.
The world of mixed feedback introduced this notion of threshold, that if the disturbance
exceeds a certain level, you want to signal the disturbance and you signal through an
event and that event is a spike and that event can be transmitted, can be communicated, there
is something happening.
I find this extremely important in every behavior and of course we could take the example
of robotics, but in fact any single control system that you look at is just jumping from
event to event.
And again, that goes back very much to the early view of cybernetics and I like the one
of Ross Ashby in particular, who developed this concept of ultra-stability, thinking
of machines as systems that switch between discrete states, like an automaton, however
each of these states being continuously regulated.
And so it is sort of a mixture between an automaton and it's a regulated automaton.
It is a concept that is very, very clear and present in the early days of cybernetics,
but there was no theory at the time to formulate that concept.
And I think that, so that has been at the core of my research to try to now use the
current theory of control to formulate what would be and how should we model such a machine.
Since you mentioned the notion of, you know, dynamics away from equilibrium, this is just
a personal curiosity.
Have you ever thought about like the links between what you're studying today and thermodynamics?
So something that you didn't like so much.
So it seems like at least locally, you're going against the principles of thermodynamics,
you're generating order in a way, I don't know if I'm making sense.
I think that thermodynamics away from equilibrium, as it was developed in the 80s and very popular
in the 90s, is indeed very much the analog of the way, you know, chemical reactions and
which at the end, those neurons are made of.
So how can chemical reactions away from equilibrium generate order, generate patterns, generate...
So at sort of a high conceptual level, yes, there is clearly a lot of resonance between
the idea of thermodynamics out of equilibrium and the idea of control out of equilibrium.
But of course, and I'm not an expert of thermodynamics, but when I discuss thermodynamics out of equilibrium
with experts, I hear that we are very far away from having a proper theory of thermodynamics
away from equilibrium.
It's probably too early to talk about these questions.
Somebody who will listen to this podcast in the future, 50 years away from now, will have
some answers, hopefully.
Since you mentioned event-based systems, and I guess one of the main applications you have
in mind are potentially event-based cameras, I think maybe we can dig into that.
So I guess those are the applications you have in mind, probably.
Is that fair to say?
Or is that more a twist?
Well, I think that when I talk about mixed feedback, people often talk about my interest
in neuroscience.
And indeed, it is because of my interest in neuroscience that I became interested in mixed
feedback and that I became sort of obsessed to try to reconcile theory, control theory
with the mixed feedback principle.
But in the recent years, and since I sort of discovered this whole community of neuromorphic
engineering and event-based sensing, it occurred to me that in fact, even away from neuroscience,
there is a huge potential of exploring event-based control.
And for instance, if you look at the book chapter of Karl Armstrong on event-based control,
his motivation comes from all possible applications of control, but neuroscience.
So it's also a way for me to sort of go back in my home country, which is the theory of
control systems, and to think away from neuroscience of the potential use of mixed feedback or
the potential use of thresholds.
And clearly, we now see an explosion of event-based sensors and event-based actuators.
So sooner or later, control engineers will be called to connect them together.
And I think it's fair to say that at the moment, we don't have a theory to connect an event-based
sensors to an event-based actuator.
The way we do it at the moment is that we interface the event-based sensors with a digital
processor.
And then we interface the output of the digital processor, maybe to an event-based actuator.
And that's how we close the loop.
But of course, it's very tempting to think that in some specific cases, we could short
circuit this interface and go straight from the event-based sensors to the event-based
actuator.
It makes a lot of sense.
Also, I guess, very trivially, potentially, just for energetic considerations.
So all of the systems that you're mentioning are very much energy, what's the opposite
of energy-hungry?
They would be not very consuming in terms of energy.
Yeah.
So this is one advantage that is very often put forward, especially nowadays in the energy
crisis that we experience, that event-based is also a potential solution to the carbon
footprint of current technology, and in particular, digital technology.
When I was a student, it was the beginning of the internet, and we really presented digital
technology and digital information as a free technology, as an energy-free technology.
And it's funny that 30 years later, especially after this pandemic, suddenly the carbon footprint
of digital technology is making news.
And everyone is sort of becoming very worried about the growing energy demand of the storing,
but not just storage, but all the devices that come with information technology.
And I think that that's exactly the vision of Kaveh Mead.
And Kaveh Mead saw that at the end of the 80s, so long ahead of his time, perhaps because
he was at the very forefront of digital technology, and he could foresee that this Moore's law
that he formulated himself would not go forever, and that there would be a time where we would
be hit by the limitation of digital technology, including the, and prime and foremost, the
energy demand of digital technology.
And I think we are living exactly in that time.
This is a good segue for me to talk about energy.
Energy from a control theoretic perspective.
So very much part of your theoretical investigations is the concept of dissipativity.
And that's one of the pillars of systems theory.
So maybe you can guide us through how does that interwine with the mixed feedback principle,
neuroscience, and your current obsession about monotonicity.
Don't get me started, because it would become a seminar.
But yeah, it's true that I think that dissipativity is a central concept of control theory, for
many reasons, but prime and foremost, because it describes this interaction between the
external and internal that I was mentioning earlier, in energetic terms.
So how does the external supply of energy relates to the internal storage of energy?
I think it's a very profound way of describing how a system or how physical systems interacts
with its environment.
It's not the only reason why dissipativity is so important.
I think that, so dissipativity is a bridge, but it's not just a bridge between the external
and the internal.
It's also a bridge between mechanics and electricity, because it's also a bridge between
the input-output description of systems and the state-space description of a system.
So it is also a bridge between the heritage of electricity, where we think of circuits
as interconnection of input-output devices, and the heritage of mechanics, where we think
of systems as determined by, let's say, Newton's law and governing the motion from an initial
condition.
Dissipativity really interconnects those two worlds, generalizing the Kalman-Yakubovich-Popov
lemma, which is perhaps the fundamental heritage of our field.
And this bridge is not just a bridge between physics and analysis, between input-output
and state-space.
It is also a bridge between physics and computation, because it is also through that bridge that
linear control theory became algorithmic.
It is fascinating that in the dissipativity paper of Ian Williams, the LMI is almost mentioned
there en passant, but in fact precedes by 20 years the reformulation of control theory
of every important control theoretic question as the solution of context optimization problem.
So yes, dissipativity is important in many ways.
And then when I moved to mixed feedback, when I moved to neuroscience, I was very frustrated
that somehow I could not use this theory, or I was always hoping for.
And I think here, perhaps I have to mention how I came to connect mixed feedback to dissipativity.
And this is thanks to a question from Malcolm Smith, my close colleague.
I had given my TED talk in 2014 about mixed feedback and, you know, praising the use of
mixed feedback.
And then I had this conversation with Malcolm and Malcolm said, by the way, how do you define
negative feedback?
Yeah, you have to, I mean, the value of such questions is, I think that most of my research
comes from such questions that are sometimes asked by colleagues, most of the times asked
by my students, by my postdocs.
It's really through those conversations that you realize that something that you found
evident and self-explanatory, in fact, is not.
And that is pushing you further into digging into the question.
So how do you define?
And the point of Malcolm was that defining what negative feedback is, is what led to
control theory.
Because after the invention of the feedback amplifier, very quickly, people start experiencing
instability with negative feedback.
How could possibly negative feedback lead to instability?
Aha, well, this is because the dynamics of the plan can, in fact, change the sign of
the feedback in the loop because of the phase shift.
And this leads to the frequency response and Nyquist.
So the whole heritage of control is in that question somehow.
Now through the question of Malcolm, I realized that there was something missing in connecting
mixed feedback to, let's say, dissipativity, because the only way you can define the sign
of a feedback loop in a nonlinear system is by thinking incrementally.
So if the feedback signal is a current signal, what determines the sign of the feedback loop
is not whether the current is an inward or outward current.
It is whether the current source has positive conductance or negative conductance.
That distinction between the sign of a current and the incremental sign of a current is something
that I didn't appreciate until I started working in that area, until I started discovering
how much it is a source of confusion in neuroscience and how much it is a source of confusion in
control.
That we, because of the heritage of the linear theory, we always tend to think of incremental
quantities and non-incremental quantities as equivalents, but they are only equivalent
for linear systems.
And this is how I started realizing that all what I knew in nonlinear control was rooted
in a non-incremental approach, including dissipativity.
So the dissipativity, the definition of dissipativity of Williams is nonlinear, but it is non-incremental.
That is, solutions are always evaluated with respect to the zero storage, the equilibrium
solution that corresponds to the minimal storage.
Instead of evaluating solutions with respect to each other.
And that has indeed become a sort of an obsession to realize that we didn't have an incremental
form of dissipativity theory.
And for many years I tried, and I don't think I'm the only one who tried to explain and
understand why we didn't have an incremental form of dissipativity, until I sort of came
up to the conclusion that in fact, we don't have a theory of incremental dissipativity
because we don't have, it's very, very difficult to think of states-based models that have
incremental input-output properties.
That gap is a total surprise to me.
It is very much, it's very close to my current research question.
And again, it is something that independently from neuroscience, independently from the
particular application that led to those questions, I think is a question, is an important question
for the field is how do you define a nonlinear capacitor?
And I've come to the conclusion that the classical state-space definition of a nonlinear capacitor
that's, for instance, was advocated by Shua and that is rarely questioned, in fact is
problematic because it gives us a model of a nonlinear integrator that is not incrementally
passive.
And this whole path from dissipativity to mixed feedback and sort of back to dissipativity
is to me, an example of how research sort of evolves and how ultimately the only way
to formulate new questions that can be extremely theoretical and fundamental is always in control
driven by very concrete questions.
So I would never have imagined to question the state-space model of a nonlinear capacitor
unless I had been pushed to refine what I meant by positive and negative feedback and
how I can sort of encapsulate these concepts that are clear to everyone because they are
everyday concepts, but if you want to turn them into a mathematical theory, you have
to work hard and then you eventually discover that the theory is incomplete.
I think this is the path of research in many problems in control theory.
Again, there is a lot to unpack there.
It was a fantastic journey just to follow your line of thought.
Maybe, OK, the first comment that I have is very curious that at the end of the day, we end up
talking so much about a sign change in a sense or whether it's positive feedback or negative
feedback. Another thing that I can extrapolate from line of thought is that, well, I'm going
to quote Sherlock Holmes from Scandal in Bohemia.
He says that it is a capital mistake to theorize that before one has data, insensibly one
begins to twist facts to suit theories instead of theories to suit facts.
And this is very much resonating with what you said.
So it seems to me also that, yeah, we are in a situation in control theory at the moment
where we very much see what Kuhn in The Structure of Scientific Revolutions predicted.
So there are phases in science where there is a growing miscontent with theories that in
some way do not satisfy, they're not able to answer questions that we do have.
And yeah, the last comment I have is that it's quite funny that we always end up talking,
at least in the background, there is always the figure of Jan Willems kind of foreseeing the
importance of so many of these questions, including dissipativity and the tension between
paradigms and puzzles.
So, yeah, that's very true.
And there is a lot in what you just said in a few words.
I agree. And I think that it's not special to our fields.
In fact, perhaps this is the value of venturing in neighboring fields.
So, for instance, I worked for maybe 10 years in optimization and manifolds and was really a
journey outside of my field, I would say, had not much to do with control.
Then I ventured in neuroscience, in neurodynamics, again, in another neighboring
community. And in all those communities, I always observed what you just described.
I think it's inevitable that a topic becomes a topic because it becomes popular.
And even if initially it emerged from a very concrete question, maybe after one generation,
it becomes a theory that is somehow independent from the question that led to the theory.
And the next generation just works on the theory.
And there is nothing wrong about that because you want to deepen the theory.
The only problem is that this by deepening the theory, you know, you create more expertise
and you create theory that is more and more detached from the original question that
motivated the theory.
And inevitably, eventually, this theory sort of detaches itself from reality.
And and at that time, I think there is indeed the danger that it becomes sort of self
referencing. But as soon as something becomes self referencing, it dies very quickly.
So I think I feel much more in peace with that phenomenon nowadays because I think there
is nothing wrong in that phenomenon.
Perhaps initially I thought, oh, but my field is bad because people are going that way.
I don't think it is specific to my field.
I think it is specific to the mechanism of research.
It just shows the importance of diversity in science.
I think of all my journeys in neighboring disciplines as sort of going into a foreign
country for a while and then going back home.
And to me, it has always been important to come back home because this is where I feel
home. And I think it's important to have a home.
But it's also by traveling that you realize, first of all, that you realize the value of
your own identity.
And nowadays, I think I have much higher appreciation for the value of control than I had
before venturing in other fields.
But it also makes you aware of the importance of diversity because it's only by, you
know, venturing and by traveling that you encounter new questions that you and this is
very refreshing. This is very important.
So there is indeed a tension, I think, and we have to be very careful about that tension.
There is no easy answer.
Otherwise, it's part of the cycle of of life in a sense.
Yeah, I mean, it seems almost an evolutionary process in a sense.
So theories do tend, as you say, to evolve on their own.
But at the same time, if they do that too much, they die.
Yeah, I think it's super interesting, potentially like the topic of another podcast
episode. I just want to close the loop maybe on on the, let's say, nonlinear control side of
things, because we didn't touch on, at least in depth, on some of the concepts that I think
are key and also made you win, for example, an Axelby Prize recently on the concept of
dissipativity. And maybe they're so and we're talking about the concept of P-dominance
for those who are not familiar with it.
There will be a link in the description and, you know, the concept of contraction, the
concept of positivity and the concept of monotonicity.
So how do all of these notions interwine and why are they so fundamental in a way?
OK, again, there is danger that I start a seminar here, but at the core of all these
questions is, again, the difference between incremental and non-incremental.
And I think it's best to start with the concept that is perhaps the most common concept to
every control theory, the concept of stability, and even more so the concept of Lyapunov
stability, which is a concept of internal stability, so state-space concept.
Lyapunov stability is non-incremental, it is stability with respect to an equilibrium
solution. The non-incremental, the incremental form of Lyapunov stability is
contraction. And contraction was introduced in our field in 98, this paper of Slotin and
Lou Miller, that I think is a turning point in our appreciation of incremental properties
in the state-space domain.
And we see nowadays, 15 years, 25 years after this, the publication of this paper, that
indeed contraction has become widely appreciated.
And I think that there is a wide appreciation of why contraction is important and perhaps
more important in many engineering questions than Lyapunov stability.
But contraction is just an incremental form, in my thinking, is just an incremental form of
Lyapunov stability.
Now, this is all about an internal concept of stability or a state-space concept.
What about the input-output concepts?
Input-output stability is well understood in the linear case.
In the non-linear case, the incremental form of input-output stability is an incremental
gain. And there is some theory about incremental L2 gains.
But a big missing bit of the control theory today is the lack of concept of incremental
passivity. That brings us back to the question I was alluding to earlier.
Why don't we have an incremental form of dissipativity?
And so the notion of incremental passivity is very well understood in an input-output
setting. If you go back to the early work of the textbooks of de Zuhr and Vidya Sagar, for
instance, passivity and incremental passivity are treated on equal foot, I would say.
But in my education, which is post-input-output theory, which is very much state-space
theory, because from the 80s, non-linear control became dominated by state-space
modelling approaches.
The incremental concept is pretty much absent of any textbooks of non-linear control.
So non-linear control theory is very much a non-incremental theory nowadays.
And I think it's because of the state-space model concept.
So my effort in revisiting incremental passivity, and that is what led me to this notion
of monotonicity. What is monotonicity?
It's incremental positivity.
So we have what are the notions of positivity?
Or we have many notions of positivity, because when we go from scalar to vectors and then
we go from vectors to operators, well, there are many ways to generalise the concept of
positivity. Passivity is one concept of positivity out of many.
And monotonicity as the incremental form of passivity is one concept of monotonicity
among others.
It's an input-output concept of monotonicity that I've discovered by going back to the
early days of circuit theory and by discovering that the person who invented the concept of
monotonicity, Minty in 1960, was precisely trying to answer a question that I've had to
answer for the last 10 years.
What is a non-linear resistor?
How do you define an element with positive conductance?
Here we go. That's also the value of re-studying history from time to time is that very,
very often you discover the answer to your questions.
You discover that they have been previously answered, but then they have been forgotten.
And so I became very interested in the input-output concept of monotonicity invented by
Minty, the fact that it then became a sort of foundation of convex optimisation.
So again, this bridge between physical modelling and computation is very much there and it
is there in the incremental form of passivity.
It is not there in the non-incremental form of passivity, which was the topic of my first
book, so of my early days in control, using passivity as a fundamental concept to, let's
say, solve stabilisation questions.
But the non-linear passivity concept, the non-incremental form of passivity, is a very
nice concept, of course, because it retains a physical meaning, but it's not an algorithmic
concept for sure.
And so the fact that a negative conductance, so a resistance with negative conductance
could be a passive element, started really showing the value of clarifying the incremental
properties of a device and not just the non-incremental passivity property of a device.
Sorry if it is too long of an answer to your question, but it's never too long, never.
I guess when you refer to conductance, you mean differential conductance or incremental
conductance. That's what you conceptually visualise.
Because I think that conductance should be understood only differentially.
The notion of chordal conductance or non-incremental conductance is not really
meaningful. Monotonicity means that the slope of your function is always positive.
But what is the meaning of positivity with respect to zero, that the graph of your function
lies in the first and third quadrants?
Yes, it is a property, but it's a property that has nothing to do with monotonicity.
And I think one would agree that for most problems, the property of monotonicity would be
far more important than the property of positivity, of non-incremental positivity.
I hear a lot of, let's say, resonance with one of your latest editorials on the IEEE
controlled magazines systems.
I should mention that Rodolf is the editor-in-chief of that journal.
I'll put a link in the description to the journal and the editorials.
The last one at this stage is about the art of the state.
And it's really a campaign to almost overthrow the state space modelling in favour of
something that is more tractable and something that is also, I would say, more robust for
the purpose of algorithmic computation.
Is that fair to say, you think?
I'm always sorry when I hear that I'm campaigning against something because it is
certainly not my intention to campaign against state space modelling.
To me, the value of control is precisely in bridging the state space world of mechanics
and the input-output world of electricity.
So my campaign is for that bridge.
It's not that we should be one-sided.
And it is for that bridge because my view of control theory or for non-linear control
theory is that today that it's very much dominated by state space, so it's very much
one-sided.
And it's not an accident that every application of non-linear control nowadays is in,
well, I should say nearly, almost application is in robotics rather than in electronics.
In fact, the contact between control and circuits disappeared in the non-linear age.
So if you open a textbook on non-linear control, there is very, very little about non-linear
circuits. And if you open a textbook about non-linear circuits, there is very, very little
about control. And my efforts to model neural systems as non-linear circuits has pushed
me to study and learn the old theory that was developed in the 70s that was all coming
from circuit theory and aiming at developing a non-linear feedback system theory inspired
by circuit theory.
And so if I'm campaigning for something, it's only to restore the importance of this
input-output approach and the value of the bridge between the input-output approach and
the state space approach. It's not at all against the, I mean, of course, the concept of
state space is extraordinarily important and a very, very important heritage of our
field.
Yeah, so I guess it would be more fair to say that you're campaigning to resurrect the
bridge that once upon a time was so evident and perhaps these days is not so much.
Yes.
I guess, again, here, from here, we could take many directions.
I have a couple of questions that I do want to ask you about, let's say, the implications
of your research in neuroscience before maybe we move on and touch on other topics.
Some of these are maybe a bit provocative and they're like the aim at fantasizing, if
you want, about what can we achieve if we understand the mechanisms by which neurons
or even the brain work?
So the question broadly would be really, what can we achieve, say, in the next decade, 20
years, 100 years, if we push forward this concept?
And, for example, I don't know, what can we say about perception?
How is it integrated or is there any hope about saying something about how consciousness
arises?
I'm not a neuroscientist, and so I don't think I'm qualified to make any prediction about
the future of neuroscience.
What I see through my colleagues who are neuroscientists is that there also there is a
resurrection of the cybernetics age.
So the whole effort of cybernetics was to think of the brain as a machine and to approach
the brain. So the British father of cybernetics, Ross Ashby, was not a control theorist, was
not an engineer. He was a psychiatrist.
And it was part of this.
It was very much at the genesis of cybernetics to approach the understanding of the brain
from an engineering perspective.
And then with the rise of molecular biology, neuroscience became a quantitative science
and it became very much dominated by a very scientific approach of describing the brain,
describing the anatomy of the brain, describing the anatomy of the neural circuits and
understanding the neural circuits from those scientific descriptions.
We see an illustration of that fact with, for instance, the emphasis nowadays on
connectomics, that, you know, as if understanding the connectome of a large network would
tell you how the network works.
And I think that nowadays there is more and more appreciation in neuroscience that if
we want to think of if we want to make progress in understanding the brain, it's not
enough to have this scientific description of the brain.
We need also to understand the mechanism of the brain.
And it's very valuable to approach those mechanisms from an engineering perspective.
And again, there is always a balance in neuroscience and in every science between science
and engineering. So in neuroscience, you have a balance between the quest of understanding
the brain and the medical desire of curing diseases.
OK, and there is a tension between those two.
But I think that the value of it's also that I love this claim of Feynman, who is
perhaps the most theoretical physicist of our time, but saying understanding is building.
So the idea that it is by building a machine that mimics the brain that we will
understand the brain.
I quite like that view and that approach.
And so that is closer to my field because control is about design.
And to me, control is design under uncertainty.
I think this is a concept that resonates very much with the current approach of thinking
of brain as producing extremely reliable functions out of huge uncertainty and
sloppiness in the components.
So how much so much variability in the anatomical components of the brain can lead to
such reliable brain functions?
I think that's a core question of neuroscience today.
That's why I think it's a control question.
And I think that as a control theorist, I see this as a key question for the future of
artificial intelligence and the future of robotics.
How can we design intelligence machines, so machines that are closer to what we
experience in natural intelligence and deal with the uncertainty and deal with the
sloppiness of the components?
And I expect a lot of progress and a lot of synergy and interaction between
neuroscience and control engineering along those lines.
So maybe we're going to cut this later.
So you mentioned at the outset.
So we're looking forward to seeing the relationship between control and neuroscience
condensing in your upcoming book with Guillaume Drion and Alessio Franchi, whose title
is, if I remember correctly, Neuromorphic Controlled Principles.
Is that right?
And we're looking forward to that.
Yeah.
You know, there are many, many books out there that are half written.
So we will see whether this book belongs to the category of published or never published
book. But no, no, I do think that this book will.
There are two reasons why you can write a book.
You either write a book because you want to learn a topic or you write a book because you
are an expert on the topic.
I like very much, I think it's Vidya Sagar who once told me that if you want to learn
about a topic, write a book on that topic.
There is no better way of learning than being forced to explaining concepts.
And again, we go back here to the tension again between teaching and researching, which is
very much intertwined, I would say.
I guess this is a good time to shift gears a little bit.
And I mean, there is a number of questions that I like to ask to our guests.
But first, I would like to maybe dig into, I would say, something like that I would call a
double life almost that you lived.
So you had time to explore optimization on manifolds in a book that potentially I think
it's your most cited publication so far.
And I remember having a conversation with you where essentially you told me that it
started as a hobby, almost it started as something that a side project, is that fair to
say? I wouldn't say a side project, but I would say as a sort of, yeah, as a journey.
So it is a side project, as you would decide to visit a country for a while and then come
back. And perhaps it's the first time in my career where I sort of venture into a
neighboring discipline because, yes, control is very much a science of optimization and a
science of feedback.
But I think that optimization is not specific to controls.
Optimization is somehow a driving paradigm in many disciplines.
So also having ventured in optimization for a while and having come back to control, I now
consider that out of the two, feedback is really what is the distinctive feature of
control theory and that control theory exists as what it is because it addresses it.
I think it's the only science in my view that really addressed the question of feedback at
its core. So venturing in neighboring disciplines showed me the value of traveling and
traveling abroad and learning another language and also appreciating how difficult it is
and how time consuming it is to learn the language of another community.
I used that skill later on when I decided to venture in neuroscience.
So it was sort of a first step.
And then perhaps realizing that by moving to neighboring disciplines, you can potentially
contribute to the discipline in a very original way.
Not necessarily being more clever than your peers, but having these different insights that
comes from the diversity I was talking before.
And so, of course, I'm very glad of the success of optimization on manifolds a posteriori
because it was totally unexpected.
And clearly working on that topic in the early 2000s was working on a very esoteric topic.
And seeing that now this topic has become widespread in machine learning and computer
vision and is, of course, very rewarding and to me, encouraging about the value of
diversity, about the value of jumping in a neighboring community and saying, OK, this is
what matters in my field.
Do you think it might be of relevance in your field as well?
And in that case, it was the role of invariance.
You know, we put a lot of attention to invariance properties when we do physical
modeling in control and the geometric thinking in control is very much rooted in an
effort to formulate questions in a sort of coordinate free manner.
And so in ways that are invariant as much as possible and approaching the design of
optimization algorithms with this particular angle was not common at all, certainly at the
time. And of course, it's of great relevance in a number of engineering disciplines where
let's say you want to computer vision algorithms to be invariance to the motion of the
camera or things like that.
We can think of many problems where invariance are of tremendous importance.
And yeah, to me, it was that's what I learned from my journey in optimization, that by
venturing in a neighboring field, well, first of all, it is very challenging because you
have to learn a new language.
Second of all, perhaps the way you can contribute there is by using your own identity and
using the diversity that you are bringing in a different community.
And so I became sort of more confident that indeed diversity is something very rewarding in
science and very important in science.
Again, there's a lot of meat to unpack there.
You're indirectly addressing one of the questions that I would have asked you before,
actually later about advice to future students, potentially.
Another thing that you touched on that I think is important is the relevance of
conceptualizing almost in a representation free manner, if that makes sense.
So that is something that is very much at the core of much of the research of Jan Willems in
the field of systems theory.
So this is actually one of the questions that I wanted to ask you.
And maybe then I'll try to close the loop on optimization of manifold.
But would it be fair to say that he was one of the most inspiring figures for you?
And if you had to name three, who would they be?
I know it's a tough question and it will definitely be do injustice to some.
Yeah, well.
There is no question that Jan Willems would be one of the three and that I think it is his
research that has been perhaps most influential on my research in exactly what you were
saying in the importance of questions and the importance of formulating a question in a
mathematically precise.
So this tension about picking your questions out of conceptual questions, like what is
positive feedback? It's a very conceptual question.
But then turning that conceptual questions into something that becomes mathematically
precise. I think that the research of Jan Willems in that regard is really remarkable.
And I have no doubt that it will be a longstanding heritage for the field for that reason.
If I have to think of other names, well, clearly I would mention my mentor, who is Peter
Kokotowicz. And Peter Kokotowicz influenced me in a very different way than Jan Willems.
It's not so much the research, I think, that influenced me, but the attitudes towards
research. And probably that today, when I have to make a decision about what to do, what not
to do, how to do something, the person that most frequently comes to mind is Peter
Kokotowicz. So what would have he done in this situation?
What would have been his advice?
And it is in that sense that I consider him as my mentor.
He certainly taught me the value of history and the fact that you cannot understand the
concept until you have unfolded the history of that concept.
I find this extremely important.
In science, we often have a negative vision on history, on the whole of history.
Oh, history is looking backwards.
Science should look forward.
And, yeah, I do think that the best way to look forward is first to look in the past
what is useful to move forward and take heritage of what was known in the past.
A third name, I'm afraid would not be a name, but I would like to mention here really the
role of my students and postdocs, including you, Alberto, because I think that and I
mentioned that earlier, that in those conversations that make you realize that you
didn't formulate clearly what you thought you were formulating clearly, those
conversations are the motor of my research.
And those conversations can, of course, happen with colleagues and with anyone.
But nothing replaces the role of students and postdocs in my experience in that
journey. So because with a postdoc or with a PhD student, you develop a sort of a
relationship over a number of years.
And so this conversation over time becomes very intimate.
And really pushes you to the heart of the matter in a way that is unmatched, I think.
So, again, the value of teaching and mentoring as the motor of research, it is
something that is very much part of my identity, I think.
That's fantastic.
Again, you keep on serving me assists about how to proceed forward, and it's always
difficult to choose because there's so many avenues that are interesting.
So I mentioned earlier that I wanted to close the loop with optimization of manifolds.
And we mentioned the value of history as well.
So I think this is a good time to ask the question of pondering about the past, the
present and the future of our field and of the fields you ventured into, if you have
any thoughts.
So I guess the question could be phrased as what are you most excited about in the years
to come? What are the technologies that we should look for?
And yeah, what are the questions maybe that systems and control theory should address?
OK, I think that it's probably clear from what I discussed before, I'm very excited by
the role of cybernetics right after the Second World War.
I'm very puzzled by the fact that this period was so short lived and that somehow the
publication of the book Cybernetics was the end of the cybernetics age because of
information theory and because of the invention of the computer that put an end somehow to
the needs of thinking of machines and animals in the same framework.
I think we are returning to the cybernetics questions and I think that this will occupy a
lot of researchers, not just in control, but also in control in the future.
I think that we have reached a stage where we see the limitations of machine learning.
We have reached a stage where we see the limitations of digital technology and we see
that the limitations of those two extremely successful developments of the second half of
the 20th century, that the limitations of those technologies come from the uncertainty
and come from the difficulty of handling and coping with uncertainty.
So this is a perfect age for control.
And I think that control will have, in my view, control has a very glorious future ahead.
First of all, because it's a very young science.
I keep thinking that control became science after the Second World War.
So it's very recently.
And that success of control is really designed under uncertainty, as I've said before.
And we have no shortage of engineering and technological challenges where we have to cope
with uncertainty.
But of course, we have to pay attention to what is happening and we have to pay attention to
how we can contribute to what is happening.
And in that regard, I have come to regard the question of feedback as really the core
question of control theory.
And I think that nowadays, perhaps a lot of research in our community has moved away from
the core question of feedback, has also perhaps moved away from the question of uncertainty
because of the prevalence of optimisation and machine learning and the fascination of what
you can do with the digital computation.
And again, don't take me wrong.
It's not that I would want to campaign against that, but it is that I think that the future
of control is in identifying that the way we can contribute to this field and to engineering
in general is really by our unique way of approaching the question of uncertainty and how
we cope with uncertainty and how we can, thanks to feedback, turn very uncertain devices
into certain functions.
This is a very fascinating picture of the future in a way, which, again, keeps on serving me
answers about questions that I have for you.
And one that I tend to ask to every guest here is about advice to future generations.
So if the question could be phrased as like, what are the most important traits that
successful researcher in our field should have?
Or is there anything that you wish you knew something about, say, when you started your
career? What sort of advice could you give to future students in control?
It's a very open ended question and it could be also like, what should they invest on, for
example?
Right. Perhaps what I would answer, it's not so much the what that matters, but the how
and the why.
And so I think you can, at least for a long, even in the PhD, there is this tension between
research and education.
You do a PhD, I often tell my students, maybe I told you that before, what I learned in
my PhD is how not to do research.
And perhaps this is the most important skill that you need to develop at an early stage
of your career, because everyone starts research with the ambition of, you know, solving
new questions, identifying the important questions.
And but what you learn by doing research is that the difficulty is not to find difficult
questions. There are plenty.
The difficulty is to respond.
The difficulty is to resonate with a question of your time and to develop skills that
eventually will give you a competitive advantage or a unique angle of attack to address
some questions. And that happens, again, as in the same way as I was talking about the
trajectory, that happens through a sequence of events.
And I think that the events themselves are not that important.
It's really that you have to learn how you respond to events and you have to find your
own identity in the way you respond to events.
And, yeah, of course, ultimately, the advice comes from Socrata, Knotis Eotan, once if
you know yourself, if you know your limitation, if you know what you can do well, you will
do well. And perhaps that's that's the most important question that we need to learn at
an early stage of our career is to try to learn something about ourselves.
Maybe the last question I have before closing this episode relates to something that I am
thinking about a lot these days, and that's the concept of creativity.
I think you're one of the most creative persons I've met so far in my life.
And so I have a question for you.
I mean, I'll start with maybe a quote from David Bohm.
David Bohm is writing the following in wholeness and the implicate order.
He writes, one prerequisite of originality is clearly that a person shall not be inclined
to impose his preconceptions on the fact as he sees it.
Rather, he must be able to learn something new, even if it means that the ideas and the
notions that are comfortable or dear to him may be overturned.
And this is something that seems to very much resonate with what you were mentioning
before. So I guess the question would be here.
Is there anything, any sort of advice that you can give to generate creativity?
Well, you are very generous, and I'm not sure I would identify myself as someone
particularly creative, but I love this quote of Daniel Barenboim, who is a great
pianist, and he says music teaches us the difference between freedom and anarchy.
And I think that scientific creativity, very much like creativity in art, is a very
fine balance between constraints and imagination.
And it seems to me, but perhaps this is personal, that it is the most constrained
type of art that leads to the biggest creativity.
So, for instance, I don't think there is a stronger illustration of that than the
music of Bach. The music of Bach is almost mathematical in a way, in the sense that it
obeys such strict rules.
How comes that throughout centuries it generates so much emotion, including in
people who have no musical education, who don't know about the constraints?
And I think that in our field, again, we are back to the fact that control is at the
same time a very mathematical science, but a science of something very concrete.
So I think that the best creativity that I see in control is the one very much
constrained by mathematics and by the rules of mathematics.
And how you find a place for novel, for innovation in those rules is a bit of a
mystery. And this is where the concreteness of the environment plays its role.
So the pianist who creates emotion from a piece of Bach might create emotion today and
totally fail tomorrow.
He might create emotion in you today, not in me and tomorrow in me and not in you.
So it's always about, and I think pianists would tell us that it's about a resonance
with the public. This resonance is really two sided.
It's not one side.
So you don't have entire control on it.
But you are the one who know the constraints, who have to operate under the
constraints. And somehow by acknowledging that those constraints are a prerequisite
for emotion and for that will happen in a somewhat uncontrolled way.
Perhaps I would think that this is a very important, at least part of creativity.
So creativity is much more than that.
But it is an element of creativity that has always fascinated me because I find that
research in control is very constrained.
You know, sorry to again talk about feedback.
I cannot help. But constraining a concept like feedback with mathematics seems like
you are. Why do you do that?
What is the value of constraining such a beautiful concept with the rules of logics?
And that is exactly the mystery of science and art.
I think that it is because the concept is not enough.
It is the communication of the concept that is as important as the concept.
And the communication uses those constraints.
So communication in science uses mathematics as a channel.
And this channel is indispensable to communicate and to exchange about the concept of
feedback that creates emotion in you and me.
But definitely a different one in you and different in me.
And if we don't have this mathematical language, we never know whether what we express
about the concept is indeed resonating with what your interlocutor thinks of the
concept. Sorry if this is too long of an answer.
It's absolutely not. I mean, it's very much resonating with, I guess, with Galileo.
So the world is written in the language of the universe is mathematics.
Since we're talking about creativity, I mean, there is abundant evidence that shows that
one thing that seems to stimulate creativity is walking.
And I know you're an incredibly avid hiker.
So in closing the episode, I thought it would be nice to ask you what is on your to-do list
there? Like, is there anything that you have planned?
Well, there the list is too long to be closed in one lifetime.
So I hope my legs can bring me to a lot of new paths.
I must say that and perhaps this has been a consequence of the pandemics that I've
discovered that walking 10 miles from home can create the same emotion as walking on
the other side of the planet.
So maybe, you know, when I was younger, my to-do list includes a very famous treks and
very challenging ones.
But I've come to appreciate that it is the activity of walking that is wonderful and
that very often and certainly in my case, I'm lucky that I don't have to walk very far
from home to find wonderful landscapes and to enjoy walking.
So I hope I will walk as much as possible and in the future and for as long as
possible. But I don't care too much where I will walk, to be honest.
But definitely, I agree that there is something quite fascinating about walking, also
for a control engineer, because we try to build walking machines.
And I also wrote an editorial about rhythm recently and rhythm are definitely a very,
very important aspect of animal machines.
And walking is a very important activity.
And I recently heard a very, very interesting conversation on the team of walking
between philosopher and a neurophysiologist.
And so the question was, is walking thinking or is thinking walking?
That resonates a lot with me as well, that certainly most of my thinking is while
walking in my personal experience.
But it is also a fact, and this was the point of the neurologist, that in fact, the more
we study the brain, the more we tend to think of the activity of thinking very much as
we think of the activity of walking and of, in fact, any other rhythmic activity of the
body. So the rhythmic nature of thinking, I think, is of great importance and again, a
natural place for control.
Yeah, so again, this is super fascinating in what we just mentioned is very much
resonating with one of your latest editorials, Clocks and Rhythms, again on IEEE
Control Magazine. There will be a link in the description.
Unfortunately, we are at the end of our episode.
It's been a wonderful journey, Rodolf.
Thanks for featuring on the show.
Thanks a lot.
Thank you very much for having me here.
It was a pleasure.
Thank you for listening.
I hope you liked the show today.
If you enjoyed the podcast, please consider giving us five stars on Apple Podcasts.
Follow us on Spotify, support on Patreon or PayPal and connect with us on social media
platforms. See you next time.