Hello and welcome to In Control, the first podcast on control theory.
Here we discuss the science of feedback, decision making, artificial intelligence and much more.
I'm your host Alberto Padoan, live from our recording studio in Lausanne.
Big thanks to our sponsor, the National Center of Competence in Research on Dependable Ubiquitous
Automation and the International Federation of Automatic Control.
You heard that correctly, we're in Lausanne.
We're not playing home this time, but we're in the neighboring French speaking side of
Switzerland for a nice event which brought together some of the most brilliant minds
out there in control and machine learning, namely the NCCR Symposium.
There will be a link in the description.
Our guest today is Jean-Jacques Zlotin, Professor of Mechanical Engineering and Information
Sciences as well as Professor of Brain and Cognitive Sciences and Director of the Nonlinear
System Laboratory at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Distinguished Faculty at
Google AI.
Welcome to the show, Jean-Jacques.
Thank you.
It's a pleasure to have you here and we're honored that you're actually accepted to be
on the show.
Maybe to break the ice, I would like to know something about you as a person.
So what do you like to do in the first six minutes of your days?
Like what's your routine?
Do you have anything specific?
Wake up slowly, yeah.
Well, you know, I don't have a specific routine, you know, so it's maybe if you want some background,
so I'm French, you know, and I moved to the US to do my PhD actually and so on.
Yeah, that's actually something that was interesting for me.
So you were born in Paris?
Yeah.
And so I was wondering whether where you grew up affected you in some way as a researcher,
not only as a person somehow.
Yeah, I feel very French and in a sense, I, you know, it used to be maybe a little less
so now, but the French training in mathematics was really strong, much stronger than in the
US.
And so when I did my PhD in the US, I never thought of staying there, you know, so but
of course, you know, places like MIT are meeting places, are places where some of the best
students of the world come and a lot of them are not Americans, actually, a lot of them
are from many, many countries and it's a wonderful place because of that, you know.
So what happened is actually, I finished my PhD very young, I was 23 and so instead of
coming back to France immediately, I was offered a position at Bell Labs, I thought, well,
you know, I should have to try that.
And then I was offered a position at MIT and then I have to try that and then ended up
staying in the US but that was never the plan.
Actually, this is something that I had read in your biography and I wanted to clarify,
you got your PhD at 23?
Yes, that's right.
How did that happen?
It started very young, you know, basically when I was an only child, which I hated and
so my mother, you know, taught me to read and write and so I ended up skipping classes
which, you know, my parents and I actually were not particularly keen on, but, you know,
so I ended up doing everything quite young, you know, and also I did my PhD quite quickly.
That's quite interesting, I mean, we could arguably say that you were a child prodigy
and also working in places like Bell Labs must have been an incredible experience.
Oh yeah, Bell Labs was a fantastic place.
It was really, you came and it was Bell Lab Research, of course, and you came and they
said, you know, we hired you because we think you're good, as everybody else, right?
And we won't ask you for five years, anything for five years.
Basically you do whatever you want, you know, you can have computers, you can have, you
know, at the time, you know, you could have computers at home was a big luxury.
You could have anything, but they wouldn't ask you anything for five years.
So and it was, and of course everybody was working like crazy, but I thought it was a
really, really nice way.
So complete freedom and creativity essentially was unleashed.
Yeah.
And actually that's a message I try to give to whenever I meet somebody reasonably high
up at Google, you know, because I think Bell Labs is in part one of the models for Google.
For me, Google is a wonderful place.
It's a mixture of Bell Labs and Club Med.
And I think with the best of both, but they care much more about evaluations and so on.
And they changed that a little recently.
And I think, you know, one of the strengths of Bell Labs is that you took really good
people and you set them completely free and you never bothered them for a long time, actually.
You never ask, you know, reports and things like that for a long time.
And this is something that I wanted to ask you later, but maybe it's, this is already
a good time to ask.
So what are your thoughts about creativity somehow?
So if you have any.
Oh, it's a broad question.
I don't know.
I mean, I think I, I guess the expression is I do my best thinking, whatever that's
worth.
I mean, you know, just walking around without, you know, without notes, without a board,
just walking around.
And I think it's very, you know, when people ask about how can they make doing math a little
easier, I always say, you know, just practice doing math without a board, without a pen,
without anything, because you get quicker at certain things this way.
It's very interesting though, that it's not the first time that I hear, you know, one
of the great thinkers that, you know, what stimulates, seems to stimulate at least creativity
is walking.
Yeah.
Walking differently, but also the fact of not doing everything in your head, you know,
because then you, I don't know, it probably trains memory or whatever, but it really helps
do things afterwards.
I find it very, very interesting.
But maybe let's go back to like the chronology if you want of Jean-Jacques Solutin.
So I was wondering what has drawn you to control?
Well, you know, when I was a kid, like everybody, I was reading cartoons, you know, and there
was one cartoon, which I didn't read much because I didn't like it very much, but which
I think was in English was Flash Gordon and, you know, I think there were better French
cartoons and so on, so I didn't, but they talked about cybernetics, you know, and for
me, I was four or five years old, you know, and so it sounded like an interesting word,
you know, and so then I wondered about that and then I learned more about cybernetics
and I figured out this was an interesting thing, you know, I read about Norbert Wiener
and all, you know, Norbert Wiener, which was really a precursor, right?
If you think of this, his book, you know, it's a science of control and communication
and human and machine, you know, you wouldn't say it any differently today, really.
You know, it has control, it has communication and it has this commonality between the biology
and machine, right?
So it's an incredibly fascinating topic and actually, it was the subject of our last episode
in this podcast, probably not the last one on Wiener, but...
And you know, so this whole, you know, cybernetics is really the common ancestor, you know, of
course, of control theory, information theory, but of course, also computational neuroscience
and AI, right?
So it's... and robotics, right?
So it's the common ancestor of all of these things, right?
It's incredible that it was condensed in a single figure like Wiener.
Oh, no, it was not, I'm saying that Wiener, when he wrote his book, you know, the title
of his book was so incredible, right?
Because it's so current still, you know, but there were other people, you know, Shannon
was involved and people like that, but Gray Walter was, he's actually the first person
who did real robots, you know, he built these little autonomous robots, which kind of moved
around, avoided each other, went to plug themselves into the wall when they were running out of
power.
And they learned, they learned a lot of things.
And that was in the late 40s, right, in the late 1940s.
And Gray Walter was actually a neurologist, that was just a hobby for him, right?
He was actually a neurologist and he built these first robots and so on.
And actually, one of the, he wrote these two famous papers in Scientific American, probably
1949, 1950, or something like that, which one was called An Imitation of Life.
And the other one was called A Machine That Learns.
And I think the first or second paper finishes with the quote saying, you know, one limit
of, basically he was building these little electronic neurons, right?
And he was saying, you know, one limit, you can predict with confidence that what would
limit things as you try to scale up is stability.
It was really interesting that he says, you know, as you're going to put more and more
of these things, it is going to be stability.
And then since he was British, he added the joke saying, you know, and therefore it's
not surprising that most smart people are also crazy or something like that, you know.
But it was kind of, it's quite interesting.
So this whole, it's kind of incredible what happened there just after the Second World
War, right?
So incredibly early in history.
Yeah.
Okay.
So from here, I guess we can take many different directions.
So we can either talk about one of your biggest ideas, and that's, I would say, contraction
among others, or let's say, take a chronological path, if you want.
I thought it would be, I don't know, curious, at least from my perspective, to give an overview
of your research.
So you started really from motivated by robotic applications, essentially.
No, I started motivated by trying to do nonlinear control.
Control for nonlinear systems, you know, I had had a teacher when I was in France named
André Fossard, and at the time, he was very familiar with research done in the then Soviet
Union.
And they had a particular way to do a kind of nonlinear control, which seemed to me very
promising.
And that was siding mode control.
But it had this problem that it had chattering, and they were not actually using for nonlinear
control, they were using for linear control, but it was, it could reasonably easily be
extended to that.
And so, you know, so I started being interesting in, you know, applying this to nonlinear control,
and we're getting rid of the chattering thing and so on.
But I quickly realized that one of the key thing, so that's getting a little technical
depending on your audience, but you take an nth order system, it's a system described
by a differential equation of nth order.
So if it was a second order system, it would be like position and velocity.
And you can always replace this nth order problem by a first order problem.
And that was really the key idea, everything else was technicalities.
And because that was the key idea, it could be extended to nonlinear systems, it could
be made the chattering, you could get rid of this switching and things like that.
And the reason, getting back to Norbert Wiener, the reason is that when Norbert Wiener explains
in his book what feedback is about, he says, well, you know, if you're trying to grab a
cup and you're a little too much to the right, you go to the left and you're a little too
much to the left, you go to the right and you end up grabbing the cup.
Or if your niece keeps asking you, I hear always you talking about feedback, you'll
probably say something similar.
And you're completely misleading that child, it's completely wrong that if you're too much
to the left, you need to go to the right, and you're too much to the right, you need
to go to the left.
That's completely wrong.
But it's true if the system is first order.
So the idea is that replacing always a system, an Nth order system by a first order system
creates an enormous simplification in everything, basically, which later on allows to do adaptive
control, adaptive nonlinear control, and so on.
Yeah, I just want to situate maybe the motivation for sliding mode control.
I guess here we're back in the 80s, pretty much 80s, between the 80s and the 90s.
And I guess there was an interest at least in control for robotic application for manipulators.
And that was based on feedback linearization, mostly, I suppose.
So that means that via feedback, we were able to change the dynamics, put it into a linear
form, and then somehow simplify both analysis and design.
The problem with feedback linearization was that it is based on exact cancellation of
nonlinearities.
And therefore, there was a need for robust methods.
And sliding mode control was definitely one solution, right?
Yeah, exactly.
And it allowed to do things reasonably simply.
I always, even people joke about that, I always tend to say, it's very simple, I want to try
to make things very simple, and so to get to the core idea and stick to very simple
things.
And, of course, when we say my ideas, I worked with many people, advisors, and especially
students and a lot of these were ideas that everybody brought.
In those days, when you were doing your PhD at MIT, there were incredible minds like Sanjay
Mehta, or Shankar Sastry, right?
Yeah, I talked to a lot of people, my advisor was Wally Vandevelde in AeroAstro, and I work
also with Shankar Sastry and others.
But the original idea of doing sliding, looking at these were actually, as I said, from my
work, not my work, my teacher in France, who was André Faussat, who actually, you know,
much in his class had talked about that, and I thought it was very exciting.
And these were really not well-known techniques anywhere, including in the US and so on.
These were kind of obscure techniques and nobody knew about it.
He happened to know about them because he had interacted a lot with these people in
the Soviet Union.
Very, very interesting.
There will be certainly an episode about the interaction between the Western world and
the Soviet world.
And what's interesting, too, is that, in the sense, in the Soviet Union, because it's highly
trained in mathematics, the fact that you had this, at the time, this discontinuous
switching, which, you know, what I didn't like, got rid of in a very simple way.
But the fact you had this discontinuous switching was actually what they thought was interesting
because they were mathematicians, you know, you could, pure mathematicians, you could
say, well, you know, you can define solutions which result from infinitely fast switching
and so on.
There was somebody, one of the big names was Philipov, who ended up being a minister of
research in the Soviet Union and so on, you know, and Utkin and people like that.
And they were fascinated by this switching.
And, you know, but from an engineering point of view, you know, except for very rare kinds
of system, the switching you don't want, you know, so, so that was that.
So now I'm curious, how did your interests shift from, say, sliding mode control towards
teleoperation, robotic manipulation, and afterwards, adaptive control?
So I did my thesis in 83, right?
And people were starting to do robotics, you know, and so that was a very natural kind
of application to use for the reasons you mentioned, right?
Because you have these nonlinear systems, and you cannot assume that you know everything,
especially with a robot, you know, if you're picking up a load, then, you know, the dynamics
changes significantly, especially if it's a good robot, like a direct drive robot and
so on.
Yeah, here, I noted down a couple of papers that are quite important, one of them being
on the adaptive control of robot manipulators with Li.
Yeah, so that paper, I think had a major impact, you know, because it basically it was introducing
several ideas at the same time, you know, it was, so this was, you know, that's why
I was saying, you know, it's not just me, it's a student, this is really joint work
with Weiping, and he did a fantastic job.
And yeah, so basically, there was this idea that the idea of a sliding variable replacing
an nth order problem by first order problem, which the point being that you can use it
also in adaptive control.
We had done that actually earlier, a year earlier with a student named Joseph Coetzee,
but for just scalar systems, you know, so when you get into robots, these become a multidimensional
systems and so on, and you have to do more than that.
So using the sliding idea, using the fact that, see here, it's getting technical a little
too, but you know, the inertia matrix of a robot is a positive definite matrix, which
allows to build it into Lyapunov function, which is something that you want to do proofs
and proofs of convergence and so on.
And so that was the second aspect.
The third one was that you had conservation of energy, and conservation of energy allowed
to do special kind of computations for those of you familiar with that, the fact that H
dot minus 2C, the derivative of the inertia matrix minus the Coriolis matrix had to be
skew symmetric, which was a matrix version of conservation of energy, which we proved
actually now it's standard and they say that in textbook in passing, but actually, I think
we were the first to prove that in that paper.
And that was itself inspired by brilliant work by a Japanese colleague of mine named
Marimoto, who, you know, showed in a little more complicated way that we ended up doing
it, but you know, showed that from physical reasons, some very simple controllers could
work for position control using basically conservation of energy.
And here there are, of course, strong ties to the concept of passivity as well.
Yes, yes, exactly.
Yeah, I mean, passivity, you know, passivity is closely related to the notion of energy
conservation is basically Lyapunov theory with inputs, you know, and so.
We're definitely going to talk about that later when I hope we have a chance to really
dig into the topic of contraction.
But perhaps continuing on our chronological journey, I somehow noticed an interest, you
know, moving from adaptive control towards neural networks and the brain.
This happens pretty much in the 90s, I would say, beginning of the 90s and the mid 90s,
definitely with a paper called Gaussian networks for a direct adaptive control, but also with
many others.
I'm curious about what sparked your interest in the brain.
Well, you know, in the, in 19, I think, 86, I went to this big conference in San Diego
where there was kind of this neural network revival and everybody was, you know, there
was Hinton and Grossberg and Hopfield and all these people there.
And they, so it was kind of survival neural networks, but they were no stability, convergence
proofs or everything was kind of heuristic.
And it was very interesting, it was clearly very exciting, and there was clearly a lot
of potential.
But people like me with a kind of a more formal background, you know, we're always wondering,
you know, why does this work?
Or when is this going to work, actually?
The question at the time was that more, why doesn't it work, okay?
But it was more, you know, trying to put some formal things in there.
And people like Grossberg, for instance, had tried to do that for certain kinds of systems.
And we were trying to do that for motion control and robotics and stuff like that.
So just to fix the ideas, what was the main idea in the paper Gaussian networks for adaptive
control?
So the paper Gaussian network, basically, it took back the ideas from the paper with
Coetzee, I was mentioning, just on adaptive nonlinear control, the paper with Weeping
Lee on adaptive robot control, and just said, okay, so typically, well, in all of these
papers, you had what's called basis functions.
So in other words, the dynamics was composed of sums of terms.
And each of these terms was always the product of an unknown parameter, like a mass or an
inertia or something like that, time a known matrix, or known vector, which represented
what you know about the physics of the system, okay, and the vector itself, depending on
the state and so on.
And so, what we wondered with Rob Sanner was that, what if we don't know these basis functions,
right?
Well, so you have these physical basis functions, but you could also have mathematical basis
functions, you know, in the absence of any information, you could say, well, you know,
I'm going to expand my function in terms of a weighted sum of coefficients times mathematical
basis functions, Fourier series or things like that, right?
But it had to be done in an efficient way, you know.
So we came up with this way of using Gaussians, because Gaussians are basically functions
of compact support.
In other words, they are basically zero outside of a certain region.
And so, when you start using them as basis functions, you're going to cover the whole
state space with Gaussians, but you're going to use at any instance, you're going to use
only a few of them, because all the others are basically zero.
And so, that was the idea.
But also, the idea was more prosaically, you know, that you have these neural networks
and some things work, some things don't, didn't, but the key aspect for us was that
you had lots of parameters, so you could do lots of things, right?
And so, if we're trying to do things systematically with lots of parameters, doing these mathematical
expansion was a very natural thing, right?
But that also got me to then talk to other people, some of which became some of my best
friends like Stéphane Mallard, to try to be, to say, well, you know, sums of Gaussians
was nice.
So, this is probably an even better mathematical way to do things, perhaps wavelets or perhaps
other things, you know.
But the sums of Gaussians is still very current and lots of people use that paper, actually.
What I found very interesting in this paper is that there is a small section where you
talk about biological plausibility.
So, at the time, you were already aware of the relevance of this work in a biological
context.
So, you literally say, although the intention in this paper is to derive stable adaptive
controllers for nonlinear dynamic systems, intuitively, the composite structure of the
above control law is compatible with the observed movements of biological organisms.
And in 1996, there is your first paper on the neuroscience letters.
So, the intermediate cerebellum may function as a wave variable processor.
So, there is really a spike, if you wish, in your interest in the brain.
So, you know, we had done this work with Gunther Niemeyer, another Berlin student, on teleoperation.
And so, in teleoperation, you have, at the time, it was called master-slave, you know,
you have a manipulator and then a local manipulator and you have a remote manipulator and you're
going to do things remotely.
And if you want to do things precisely remotely, you need some kind of force feedback.
But if you have now, if you'd have this with, it means you have a feedback loop now between
the local and the remote and a pure delay in the feedback loop in both direction, which
is a perfect recipe for instability.
And so, what we had shown, which was inspired but also by some work of Anderson and Spong,
we had shown that you could get the system to not naturally generate instabilities by
making the transmission work like a flexible beam.
And mathematically, one very simple way to do that is that instead of transmitting through
the transmission with the usual variables, like positions and velocities and so on,
you transmitted composite variables, which were mixtures of forces and velocities.
And doing so, you mimicked a transmission line with, and the transmission line of passive
transmission lines.
So, if you put the transmission line on the table, it's not going to explode because there's
no source of energy, right?
And so, that was this idea of getting passivity, which as I mentioned, some early work had
done, but using this idea of just sending the right variable through this transmission
line.
And it also started to be a little of a theme because the sliding variables were composite
variables, were sums of variable.
And these were different sums of variable that, you know, really helped.
And we also, there was another article actually where we, I talked at that time to also people
in neuroscience, and they said, you know, understanding motion control is very hard
because you have this mess, what you measure, it's not clear if it's position, it's not
clear if it's velocity, it seems to be kind of this mixture, you know, biology is dirty.
And you know, my point was, no, no, it's not because it's dirty, it's because using the
right composite variable, right?
It's actually simplifying things by doing things this way, you know.
And so, that's also led to that paper about the cerebellum and so on.
But because if you think of it, right, from the brain to the hand is at least a tenth
of a second for the message to go.
And similarly, the other way back, right?
And so, you have very much this problem that you have in teleoperation with a pure delay,
okay?
Incidentally, the work we have done with Nimaya was interesting for a different point of view
is that it's very easy with a delay to get an instability, even if the delay is really
small.
Conversely, using these wave variables and so on, with small delay, the delay becomes
completely transparent.
So, instead of, you know, spending your time fighting the stability of the system, because
you know, there's an operator on the other side, right, so you can, but instead of spending
your time fighting the stability of the system, you can have something which is naturally
stable and at small delays is completely transparent, you know, so.
That's fantastic.
And is there also a message behind this that, you know, using these variables, we gain some
predictive capability?
Yeah, yeah.
So, then you can interpret these variables, right?
So, some of these variables are like predictions, and some of these variables kind of add damping,
right?
So, you can interpret what these variables do.
But yeah.
Fantastic.
And of course, I mean, the brain is dealing with very slow components, right?
So, in other words, the brain is doing all these things, you know, famous basketball
players and so on, so much better than, you know, robotic basketball players.
But still, they're using brains where neurons react about a million times slower than transistors,
right?
So, humans are very good at real-time motion, although they're dealing with desperately
so slow hardware, okay?
And very energy efficient also, in terms of...
And very energy efficient.
So, that's the other thing, right?
So, maybe we'll talk more about learning, deep learning and so on later on.
But you know, so, when you do deep learning or things like that, you literally put batteries
of computers near electric dams, right?
Because you need so much energy.
But the brain is using 20 watts, right?
Which is much less than any light bulb, right?
And incredibly interesting, and we're definitely going to talk about that maybe towards the
end of this episode.
But first, I would like to dig into perhaps one of your most important contributions.
So, in 1998, you published together with Winfield Lummiller on contraction analysis for nonlinear
systems.
So, here I think we owe to the audience a definition of what contraction is, and perhaps
even what stability is.
Yeah.
So, Winfield was a super brilliant German student, and he had the very much European
training as I had actually.
So, you know, he happened to be really good at many, many things, and in particular at
fluids.
It was the time when I was starting to try to do catching with robots, you know, and
we're trying to throw paper airplanes and catch them.
And we realized there was no way to build predictors or observers for nonlinear systems,
which were reliable.
And the idea of throwing a paper airplane is that it always flies differently, and it
can fly up or it can fly down.
It can fly straight, and you want to be able to predict that in real time.
And we realized there was like zero techniques to do that.
And so, we wondered with Winnie about Lyapunov, and Lyapunov was, as we mentioned a little
earlier, Lyapunov theory, which for me, Lyapunov theory is one of the most brilliant idea in
the history of science, right?
But Lyapunov theory is based on, precisely because it's so simple, it's based on the
idea of virtual physics, right?
It's based on the idea of basically creating mathematically something which could be interpreted
as physics, it's a virtual world.
But it's basically virtual mechanics, it's virtual kinetic energy and things like that.
And so, we wondered, you know, what if we try to do virtual fluids, right?
So that was basically the original idea.
And Winnie started to do a little, a bunch of, you know, simple simulations where we
used just the divergence of the system.
So as simple as you can get for virtual fluids, it already worked really well.
So we started to build on that, you know, obviously the divergence, which for the aficionados
is also the trace of the Jacobian, which is the sum of the eigenvalues of the Jacobian.
The fact that the divergence is negative shouldn't be enough to guarantee that you always tend
towards one trajectory.
It just guarantees that volumes shrink.
So we tried to make it more explicit to show that, to give conditions in which any two
trajectories of a system would tend towards a single trajectory that didn't have to be
an equilibrium, but it had to be in the trajectory, right?
And also, so in a sense, it was a kind of Riemann joining forces with Lyapunov, right?
Because we had to define the distances in the right way and distances involves metrics,
you know, the original name of contraction actually was metric theory and we changed
it to contraction.
So it's very much Riemann coming to help to build Lyapunov-like functions.
This is incredibly interesting.
I guess some intuition for the audience is that contraction guarantees that small disturbances
or initial conditions are asymptotically forgotten.
The way it's defined, it's a concept that is defined in terms of the differential dynamics,
right?
So it's small displacements.
So we can situate this idea, I mean, in history as ancestors, I would say the calculus of
variation.
Yeah, yeah, the calculus of variation.
So originally, you know, we paid a lot of care of, you know, we kept defining these
differential displacements and so on.
And you know, we paid a lot of care saying, well, you know, these are well-defined mathematical
objects and so on, because actually that's what the review says.
What are these things?
These are approximations?
No, no, they're not approximations.
They're just differential displacements.
So these are exact relations, like the way you say d cosine theta equal minus sine theta
d theta, right?
It's an exact relation between differentials.
This can be well-defined mathematically.
This is actually what is used in the calculus of variation.
And from our point of view, it's also what was used in fluids, right?
That's exactly what you're doing all the time in fluids.
So that's what we did.
And it, you know, took a few iterations to get to the right formulations, but basically.
And you know, in passing, it had...
So I must say, either we were lazy or modest, I'm not sure.
But there's a section in that paper where we give extensions.
And each of these extensions is put as a remark.
And after that, people wrote entire papers on this single remark.
For instance, we show that if you have a contracting system driven by a periodic input, then you
tend towards a state of the same period.
And it's very easy to show, but it shows also the power of the formulation.
But it's funny.
So lots of people took these remarks and then wrote papers.
We showed also that the way we define contraction was based on the Euclidean norm, but you could
pick other norms, one norms or infinity norms and so on.
And you've got equivalent definitions of contraction, but some of which may be easier to compute
in some contexts.
I have lots of questions in this respect.
I mean, maybe one provocative question is why somehow the framework of contraction?
So why working on tangent spaces?
Why is it possible that we can study nonlinear phenomena in such an easy way through essentially
linear techniques?
So why is it?
Yeah.
So we wonder about that, especially, you know, Winnie, of course, had taken my class and,
you know, one of the things, any nonlinear systems class says, you know, says, well,
nonlinear is very different from linear.
You know, if you take a linearization at a point, it doesn't tell you what the nonlinear
system is doing.
So we wondered about that.
But then we quickly realized, actually, the key is that it's not linearization at a point.
It's linearization everywhere.
So it's as if, you know, you take a function and I give you the slope everywhere and I
give you the value of the function at a point.
And of course, you know the entire function.
It's not the same thing as giving you the value of the point of the slope at a point
is the value of the function at some point and the slope everywhere.
And here it's so it's based on the Jacobian everywhere.
So from that point of view, that was not a mystery.
It's just based on that.
But the fact it was still based on linearization allowed to use a lot of matrix algebra and
so on that you normally don't use in nonlinear control.
And so that was the.
This very problem actually has some history in control itself, like we all some people
know at least about the Kalman conjecture.
So if I have a system, a linear system, and I have feedback, some kind of nonlinearity,
and I take the derivative of this nonlinearity and I postulate that the overall resulting
system is stable for every nonlinear gain in a certain, let's say with certain bounds,
then the conjecture was that you can actually prove stability.
And this conjecture was disproved.
Yes.
But somehow here the intuition is that if you work with the state really, and you work
with the Jacobian everywhere, then you're capable of showing a much stronger condition.
Yes, exactly.
Precisely because you're working with the state, you know.
For instance, it's not like passivity, which is an input-output thing and so on.
It's really fundamentally a function of the state.
And it's using the fact that, you know, you have this common metric everywhere.
And so the equations end up linear, to be linear in the metric, but they do involve
the time derivative of the metric, which itself depends on the state and so on, right?
So, shifting gears again on the topic of contraction, but shifting gears in the sense that so far
we've only talked about stability, but most problems of interest out there are actually
away from equilibrium.
And so Ilya Prigogine, Nobel Prize in Chemistry in 1977, says that entropy is the price of
structure.
So I'm wondering, what is the relationship between contraction and thermodynamics or
in general contraction and instability?
Okay, so it's funny you ask that.
So let's start with instability, okay?
So one of the, often when I talk, give general talks about contraction, I talk precisely
about instability and saying, well, you know, there's lots of cases where you want instability,
but the fact that you have contraction analysis gives you a much more precise way of understanding,
you know, what are the limits of stability and so on, so of mastering instability.
So I think control instability is really important, right?
If you have a military aircraft, these military aircraft move very quickly because basically
their center of mass is very close to the center of lift, so they're nearly unstable
or some of them are frankly unstable.
And because of that, you can basically throw them into an instability and then catch them
through control and it can go really fast, okay?
I had mentioned Gunther Niemeyer, we did another paper on how to open an unknown door, you
know, because we were tired of having, seeing these papers where you had, you know, groups
of engineers working really hard to open an unknown door with a robot.
And if you think of it, if you grab a door handle and try to open the door, it should
be very easy because the door is a one-dimensional object, it moves in one direction.
And so if you create an instability, which is very easy, it's X dot equal X, right?
If you create an instability, then you're going to move in the right direction.
You don't need to know exactly, it could be a hatch, you don't need to know exactly its
positions, its orientation and so on.
Just creating this instability, you'll move in the right direction and it really works
really well, okay?
So that's another case where exploiting instability is important and makes things easier.
We had done also some work with Randy Douglas and Uli Huttishauser on graph coloring, okay?
And here, this was more in the style of machine learning in the sense we have a good idea
why it works, but we haven't proved formally why things work.
But suppose you're trying to do graph coloring, so you have a graph and you're trying to have
each node of the graph to be of colors different from its neighbor, okay?
And you can show mathematically, you can always do that with four colors, but how do you do
it?
What's the algorithm?
So there are very complicated ways to do that and we just tried something based on instability
which really worked really well, which was when each of the nodes was a winner-take-all.
So in other words, it chose a color and it kind of pushed the other nodes away, okay?
It chose a color and pushed it, and the other node was also choosing its color and pushing
the others away and so on.
And this, actually, you converge very, very quickly to a solution to the graph coloring
problem, okay?
Again, exploiting instability, okay?
It's fantastic.
This is kind of an opposite problem of synchronization almost.
Yes, it's exactly the opposite problem of synchronization, yeah, yeah.
And you're absolutely right.
And so, the relationship with Prigogine, it's funny you mentioned that.
I met Prigogine, I had the long talks with, well, not long talks, at least one long talk
with Prigogine.
And Prigogine was one of my heroes when I was, just before I came to the U.S., actually,
because I was very, very interested in self-organization and non-equilibrium systems and things like
that.
And this notion of entropy production.
But if you look at the results, you know, you have this interesting result, which says
that basically, if you have systems away from equilibrium, but still in some kind of linearized
range, then they minimize entropy production, okay?
So it's kind of a general law, but it's a very, it applies to only a very, very specific
kind of system in a very small range.
And then Prigogine and Nicolis and Lenzdorf tries to extend these results to the general
case and then they have this rather inelegant, which they recognize themselves, extremely
inelegant condition, which it's a mathematical condition that doesn't mean anything physically,
you know.
It's funny because actually, currently, we're doing PD versions of contraction with a very
good math undergrad.
And we're trying to solve exactly that problem.
We're trying to, which I'm not, I'm pretty sure we won't, because, you know, this has
been an outstanding problem for 50 years.
You know, what is the generalization of this Prigogine relation, but, you know, using contraction
and stuff like that.
Absolutely fascinating, absolutely.
Maybe one thing that we should mention about contraction is that it has a lot of nice properties.
So it is modular, I guess that's perhaps the most important property.
It's modular because it applies to non-autonomous systems.
So in other words, it applies to systems of inputs.
And because it applies to the system of inputs, you can play Lego with it, you know, you can
start putting things together.
And so it has very nice modularity properties, you can build very large contracting systems
out of simpler elements by using some simple rules, basically.
And this actually, when we developed that at about the same time, literally at about
the same time, actually, there were biologists at Harvard who, Mark Kirshner notably, who
were developing this idea of facilitated variation, the idea that in biology, there are core components
like DNA replication or sexual replication, things which has been fine-tuned for a long,
long time and then stayed more or less the same, like DNA replication, for instance.
And that evolution is working basically on how you connect these things.
And it's very, very much the same message as contraction, right?
So you have these building blocks, and then you're going to connect them and you're going
to create these large systems.
And you just have to make sure that how you connect these building blocks verifies some
simple rules that guarantee contraction of the entire system.
And so actually, we have a paper this year in NeurIPS called RNNs of RNNs, you know,
we're doing exactly that, you know, we do a contraction analysis of individual recurrent
neural networks.
And then we just pick lots of these networks and we connect them.
We just learn the connections.
And actually, we get to state of the art in some standard test problems, you know, just
doing that.
Yeah, I guess modularity is really a key property, because then it allows you to go across scales,
reason across scales.
Yeah, yeah, it allows you to go across scales.
And it's, of course, fundamentally something that nature uses, right?
For all the good reasons that, for instance, Herbert Simon explained, and, you know, for
people who don't know, Herbert Simon is both a Nobel laureate in economics and one of the
founders of AI.
And he has this very, very famous paper called The Architecture of Complexity, where he explains
the role of modularity, the role of multiple time scales, too.
Yeah, maybe in closing on the topic of contraction, I thought we should mention also the companion
paper, Modularity, Evolution and the Binding Problem, where you do relate the concept of
contraction to really somehow its biological, both motivation and application.
Is that fair to say?
Yes, yes.
So that came out of a series of lectures I gave at the Collège de France that year.
And on trying to start understanding the brain from the point of view of dynamical systems,
right?
So the problem is, you know, when you look at a scene or whatever, some parts of your
brain are processing vision and these parts of themselves, some different subparts processing
edges and colors and so on, and some parts are processing sound and so on.
And so different parts of your cortex, in that case, are processing different parts
of what's going on.
But at the same time, you know that all of these parts, you know, are talking about common
event, okay?
What you see corresponds to what you hear and so on.
So that's called the Binding Problem, you know, how is this done?
And you know, we showed a possible mechanism, if you want, on how it's done.
We also did that in the paper with Kwong Tham, you know, on synchronization and things like
that.
But also, on the topic of contraction, there was an extra idea, which we did with one way.
And again, for the aficionados, we talked about, in the contraction paper, we talked
about virtual displacement, which is the term used in fluids.
But later on, we call them differential displacements, not virtual displacement, because the term
virtual we used for something else, which was this paper with one way, which was talking
about synchronization of oscillators or dynamical systems in general.
But the idea is actually quite simple, but we think quite powerful and fits very well
with contraction.
The idea is that, for instance, if you take two oscillators, two identical oscillators,
and you're trying to show that they synchronize, so neither of the oscillators is contracting,
because if you pick arbitrary and initial conditions, you end up on the limit cycle,
but you know, you will not catch up.
The trajectories won't catch up with each other on the limit cycle, so neither of them
is contracting.
But the idea is that you can exhibit a virtual mathematical system.
You can construct a virtual mathematical system, which is contracting and happens to have these
two trajectories as particular solutions.
And because these two trajectories happen to be particular solutions of this virtual
contracting system, they have to tend towards one another.
In other words, the two oscillators have to synchronize.
So it was a very simple idea, but it allowed to do a big jump in the applications of contraction,
if you want, because you were not just doing convergence to a common trajectory, you're
starting to be applying it to synchronization and so on.
For systems which are not contracting, but you're using contraction to show synchronization.
Yeah, so literally, it's using contraction in order to converge to attractors that are
more general than a particular trajectory.
Exactly.
But we're using this idea of a virtual system.
So in other words, the proofs end up being very simple, you know, say, consider this
virtual system.
Obviously, it has these two systems, this particular solution, and obviously, it's contracting.
So these two solutions tend towards another, right?
I am familiar with that proof.
It's essentially where you show that for either sufficiently strong coupling, or whether
the system contains sufficiently many agents, let's call them agents, then essentially you
achieve convergence.
Yes, exactly.
But the sufficiently strong coupling happened to be small, right?
So in other words, it's not for infinite coupling, you know, so you can get a minimal bound for
which this happens, you know.
And this was a result I had a hard time convincing my mathematician friends, although I saw the
proof was correct, right?
Because basically, a lot of the work which had been done before on synchronization was
always near the limit cycle, right?
And you never had these kind of global results.
And this sounded too simple to be correct.
But actually, it was correct.
It was like, yeah.
Yeah, because in general, it's a hard problem.
Yeah.
So I won't say who it was.
But you know, Jean-Jacques think, you know, it can't be true, it says, well, you know.
Turns out it is.
Actually, this is a good assist for maybe the next topic.
So in the years 2010, more or less, you start focusing on synchronization.
And there's another important paper, in my opinion, called How Synchronization Protects
from Noise.
And I think this is a topic that is worth spending some time on.
So what does that mean?
Basically, a lot of things that you do in science, especially in neuroscience and so
on have to do with taking average measurements.
Like in the brain, you know, if you do fMRI, it's actually spatial averaging of a lot of
things, right?
But the notion that averaging is a good thing, and in particular, it cleans up the noise.
Well, so fMRI comes from the technology.
But the fact that people assume that averaging is a good thing comes from a linear point
of view.
So if you have a linear, if you measure, if you have signals, each of which has noise
and you take an average, then you clean up the noise, okay?
And if you take linear dynamical systems and you drive them with signals which have noise
and you average the output, you also clean up the noise.
But if you take nonlinear dynamical systems and drive them with input without noise, you
don't clean up the noise.
You get a signal that looks reasonably clean, but has no relation to what you're hoping
to get, which is the noise-free signal.
And so what this paper was showing is that, so you have these basic systems, you drive
them with inputs plus noise, you take the average at the end, it doesn't work because
the systems are nonlinear.
However, if you synchronize the systems and then take the average, now you're cleaning
up the noise, okay?
So in other words, the fact that these networks now work as a team allows to get, for nonlinear
systems, the noise averaging properties you would expect for linear systems.
But of course, you can ask the question in reverse.
So it's saying, well, you know, so we're taking fMRI and we're assuming that it means something.
And actually it does because it does correlate to behavior and so on and so on.
So it probably means there is a synchronization phenomenon in the things we're measuring,
because we know if, well, that's not probably the only possibility, but it's the most plausible
possibility, right?
That there is a synchronization phenomenon which allows this average signal to actually
be meaningful.
Okay?
So that's the...
One here could also speculate that that's also how biological systems work in general.
So how do they function so reliably out of components that are, in general, not so robust?
Exactly.
And between neurons, for instance, you have the usual synaptic connections, but you also
have electrical signals and all sorts of things.
In the same years, I guess this somehow motivated you to think of networks.
You managed to get the cover article of Nature.
I wonder whether you are the only person in control who managed to do that or is there
anybody else?
I haven't checked, but I believe so.
I believe so.
And it was on the controllability of networks, you know, and actually I sent the paper to
Rudy Kalman, who was still alive at the time, you know, and said, you know, it took 50 years,
but it was about time that, you know, controllability is finally on the cover of Nature.
So how did you manage to do that?
And also what is the paper about?
Actually, my colleague and friend Laszlo Barabasi moved to Boston and we were saying, well,
you know, it would be fun to start doing something together.
So he didn't know anything about control.
So I started explaining some basic things about control and, you know, of course, the
basic questions are controllability, what understood for linear systems and so on.
It would be fun if we could do controllability of network.
And Laszlo said, well, you know, it's plausible that we could do something because after all,
this is just an algebra question and networks are very good at that.
And so, but we thought by the end of this launch, we thought it would be interesting.
Well, we thought it would be nice to do, but trivial, because it would probably end up
being hubs.
Okay.
The question of whether, which nodes do you need to control to control the entire thing
would probably be the most connected systems and which are called the hubs, right?
And that would be it and people would say, yeah, fine.
But we actually very quickly realized actually by the evening that this was not the case
at all, because if you have hubs, which are, they create symmetries.
And because they create symmetries, it means that you cannot independently control the
other nodes.
So you don't want hubs at all.
You want something else.
And so then we hired a postdoc, well, more precisely, Laszlo had this postdoc who just
came to his lab.
And so we asked him to work on this very, very good postdoc named Yang Liu.
And so he did most of that work.
And Laszlo is extremely good at writing papers.
So he did a very beautiful writing of this paper.
And so when it was accepted in Nature and it was accepted as a full article, which was
funny because Laszlo had other articles in Nature, but it was his first full article.
He was very proud of that.
We said, well, you know, for me, it was my first article in Nature.
And so we said, well, you know, we might as well try to get the cover.
So we worked hard to get the right picture and the right background to get the cover.
And we did get the cover, which was fun.
You might as well.
And I should mention that you also got the cover of the proceedings of National Academy
of Sciences.
Yeah, exactly.
So then we wrote observability and we didn't have to do any work to do, they gave us the
cover, which was fine.
One sentence that I really loved from this abstract was, from the abstract of the previous
paper, was that the ultimate proof of our understanding of natural or technological
systems is reflected in our ability to control them.
So Feynman would have said to build them, but you actually advocate to control them,
which is fantastic.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
And I think, you know, I'm not sure who wrote the sentence, probably Laszlo, it's, yeah,
absolutely.
Yeah.
Another consequence, I would say, that is worth spending time on of this paper is that
you managed to connect something that very much has to do with graph theory, with questions
that are very much control theoretic.
So the matching problem and controllability of a network.
And what I found very fascinating was that as a consequence of this paper, ablation studies
had been done on C. elegans, this worm, in order to study its locomotory properties,
essentially, and how to pinpoint what are the neurons that are involved in locomotion
of this nematode.
And somehow you managed to predict that out of a network that is pretty considerably big,
all of the neurons that are involved in locomotion, and even find a new one, right?
So I thought that this is really an incredible case study that shows the power of what control
still has to say on so many different topics.
Yeah.
I also wanted to mention on the context of synchronization, there was one extra idea,
which was also very biological, but turned out to be, I thought, very interesting, which
came from bacterial biology.
When you have work in particular by Bonnie Bassler, when you have a bacterium, suppose
it's a bad bacterium, it's trying to bother its host or kill its host, to do that it needs
to replicate.
Because if it's by itself, it's not going to do anything.
So it needs to replicate.
And at some point, when there's enough of them, they switch the behavior and they get
into a more aggressive behavior towards the host.
And the question is, how do they know there's enough of them?
Nobody is supervising what's going on, okay?
And so they know because they send chemicals in the environment, which are called autoinducers.
Each of them sends a chemical and each of them measures the total amount.
And that way, they can know how many there are and so on.
But of course, it's also a very nice form of synchronization, because you can show it's
a one line proof that if you're trying to, if you have sub elements, and you're trying
to connect them all to all, an equivalent way of doing that is to create a common signal,
which is basically the sum and sending back to everybody else.
So computationally, it's very efficient, because instead of having order n square connections,
as you connect all to all, you implement the exact same computation with only order n connections.
So it's a very interesting computer science idea, if you want that bacteria found.
But also it allows to build, to understand how things synchronize very, very simply using
this idea of a virtual system.
So that's, you know, it's kind of quorum sensing idea.
We used a lot after that.
It's a way to count, essentially, count each other.
It's a way to count and it's a way to synchronize, you know, using the environment.
And we showed later on with a paper with colleagues at Stanford, Max Schwager and his group, that,
you know, when you do robotic manipulation of a common object, you can use exactly the
same idea where the common object serves as the environment.
And it becomes a synchronization problem.
Maybe we should shift gears and now come to your most recent work.
So lately you've been shifting your interests towards, I would say, optimization and machine
learning and somehow even going back to the origins where you were interested in adaptive
control.
So what are the, what keeps you busy these days?
Yeah.
So the bridge of machine learning.
So we started doing that with Rob Saner, of course, but now there's many more things happening
in machine learning.
I just want to mention, just to wave the flag that, you know, one of my heroes in control
theory is Brian Anderson, who is a famous Australian control theorist, did a lot of
work in adaptive control.
And the latest algorithms on deep learning, which are based on score-based diffusion,
are directly inspired by a paper he wrote in 1982, which is, of course, in the references.
But it's, it's actually, it's very interesting that, you know, he wrote this paper in 1982
and now it's used to, to have these systems where you say, you know, draw me a dog in
a sushi house and draws you a dog in a sushi house and it's, and it's fundamentally using
Brian's paper, actually.
So yes, we started doing things with Saner and of course, I mean, even when I was interested
about Pregogine, I was interested in physics of life and stuff like that, right?
But now there's so many things happening with, with machine learning.
So as your things are going so fast and, and for me, this interaction with Google was
fantastic because, you know, first of all, it's a lot of young people.
So you, you, you feel more excited because of that.
And you know, it's really kind of reminded me of Bell Labs and, you know, the excitement
that everybody has with a lot of resources at the same time.
Okay.
And so, so you have all of these algorithms and you're trying to make them, one way to
say this is, okay, when you're taking an airplane, the airplane is rated at 10 to the
minus nine, which means that there's only one chance in a billion that something will
go really wrong in the next hour.
Okay.
The whole thing is rated at 10 to the minus nine.
Now how would you like to board an airplane and somebody would say, well, welcome aboard.
You'll be happy to know that the control system for this airplane was designed using the latest
neural networks.
And as a result, we have a 96% chance to actually land in San Francisco.
That wouldn't be, so the question is, you know, how can you start building guarantees
around these things, you know?
And of course, it's not just guarantees, it's how can you make them more efficient?
You know, this, you know, is a question of data efficiency.
How many examples do you need to, to distinguish a lion from a dog, you know?
And a little girl needs two, right?
But a machine needs much more, okay?
So both understanding questions of, you know, what kind of guarantees can you give?
You know, the words these days is certificates, right?
What kind of guarantees can you give?
But also, I think, even more interesting, you know, how can you make them much more
powerful, much faster, much more efficient, much more data efficient?
I have many questions in this area.
I mean, perhaps one would be, again, biology will play a role, you think, in...
Sorry?
Will biology play a role, you think, in becoming more efficient?
Possibly.
We have to remember, though, that, so I think so, first of all, but we have to remember
that in evolution, the brain spent a lot of time fighting the fact it was dealing with
these very slow components, right?
So time delays are very fundamental in what the brains are doing, transmission delays,
computation delays, and so on.
And so in machines, we have much less of this problem.
So of course, we should be inspired by the brain, because there's lots of really good
ideas in there and so on.
But it's not clear that we're really solving the same problems, okay?
So yes, so I think biology will have a role, but it's important to realize that its constraints
were different, okay?
Another question that I have is, what is the role of contraction in optimization?
So we did this paper with Patrick Wintzing recently, where we kind of looked at just
gradient descent from a contraction point of view.
The paper is called Beyond Convexity, because a lot of time, the reflex when you try to
say, well, you know, I have gradient descent, when will it converge?
Well, let's say it will converge if the function is convex, okay, fine.
But actually, this is a set of measures zero in the set of all the functions that will
converge, because what you can very easily show that if you have gradient descent and
you're trying to impose that this gradient descent is contracting in an identity metric,
then you get exactly the condition that the function is convex.
But it could be contracting in any metric, and it would still tend to a unique equilibrium
point, which would have to be in the minimum.
So in other words, when you say, does my gradient descent converge, a sufficient condition is
not that it's convex, it's clearly sufficient, but a much, much more general sufficient condition
is that it's contracting in some metric, which doesn't have at all to be identity, okay?
So that's kind of the first point.
The second point, of course, is that because you can use contraction, then you can start
building combinations of these things, you know, series and feedback and so on.
And in some sense, you know, backprop is a hierarchy of such gradients, right, is a series
of such gradient and things like reinforcement learning or more or adversarial learning are
very much a feedback version of some such gradients, okay?
And then we showed this thing, which we thought was kind of amusing.
I hadn't played much with semi-contraction, in other words, even with Winnie and so on,
we hadn't played much with that.
But by the way, a side point, I must say I'm honored that I had very few students because
I hate writing grants and so on.
So I had very few students, but I'm honored that a lot of them are interested in still
working with me years after that.
And so we still work with Winnie and so on, for instance.
But getting back to that point, we had very rarely looked at semi-contraction.
So what's semi-contraction?
It's when the distance between a trajectory does not increase, okay?
It doesn't mean it decreases, but it doesn't increase.
You can write it in terms of contraction, instead of having a contraction rate, which
is you have zero, okay?
So it's very, very easy.
So what we wondered with Patrick Wensing is, so suppose you have a gradient system which
is semi-contracting in some metric, okay?
So in other words, you know that the distances between any two trajectories in that metric
do not increase.
What can you say?
And you can show that, so you have this gradient system, it's semi-contracting in some metric.
You can show that automatically it will tend towards a global minimum, that this global
minimum will in general, of course, not be unique, but that all global minima will be
path-connected.
And so in other words, if you have a gradient system contracting in some metric, you get
exactly the topology that you get in deep learning.
In other words, you have lots of solutions, good solutions in these very over-parameterized
systems.
And all these good solutions are connected by path, which are also good solutions, okay?
And so, and you get that simply by imposing that the system is semi-contracting in some
metric, which of course gets to conjecture, which I'm not sure is correct or not, but
that in these over-parameterized system, it's reasonably easy to get a metric that verifies
this condition, because of course you have a very large dimensional system and the metric
varies as n squared, right?
So there's a conjecture if you want, I'm not sure it's correct, it's really a conjecture,
that as you get into the very high dimensional system, this condition that the system is
contracting in some metric becomes easier and easier to verify.
And that's therefore why you have all these deep learning things at work.
It's very, very interesting and very fascinating.
I don't really have a complete intuition about this.
Maybe, can you help us, I don't know, with an analogy, try to digest why this is the
case?
No, no, as I say, it's a conjecture, right?
But it's interesting to see if you just say I have a gradient or a natural gradient system
and just impose semi-contraction in some metric, then I get exactly the topology of equilibrium
and so on I get in deep learning, which people have noted but don't know how to prove, right?
And I was just asking, in terms of ideas that intuitively help us showing that semi-contraction
implies this path connectedness, is that related to LaSalle?
It's really the proof, right?
So in other words, suppose that you have two equilibria and you start with a path between
the two equilibria, which is not an equilibrium path, just a path, and you'll just let it
deform through the dynamics, then you'll end up having a deformed path between the two
equilibria and you can show it will tend towards a steady state.
And at the steady state, the gradient is zero, which means that the cost on all the paths
has to be the same.
And therefore, they're all global minima.
And you can show that semi-contraction basically guarantees that as you take this original
path and let it transform, things don't split.
Maybe, you know, moving towards the end of this episode, another question that I really
like to ask to our guests is advice to future generations.
So if you were a student today, what would you invest on?
Oh, invest on?
Well, I'm not sure about advice to future generations, but, you know, I mean, the obvious
thing to say, which I guess we'll get from everywhere, is that you should pick up something
that you're really interested in, you know, you should pick up something that you're keen
to work on, you know, on weekends and things like that, right?
You shouldn't care at all what other people say, because generally, you know, contraction
as in many things, right, went through the process of, you know, people saying it's wrong,
and it's trivial, then I invented it, right?
And it's something very, it's something you see all the time in all cases.
So I would pick, you know, things that you're really interested in.
My particular bias, but I'm not sure I should advise, give this advice to young people today,
but my particular bias is that you shouldn't worry much about funding.
I never did, okay?
As a result, I had very, very few students, a lot of them were actually self-supported,
they had grants from their country or things like that.
But as a result, I never spent time in Washington trying to convince people who didn't have
the background that what I was doing was interesting.
So I'm not sure if I have any record of anything, but if I had a record, it would probably be
the number of citations per dollar, because the dollar is generally zero, okay?
So that I would recommend, or at least, you know, try to carefully select students, and
I was very lucky with the few students I worked on, who are all super brilliant and really
do work, okay?
Don't spend time writing grants and so on, but that's my point of view, okay?
Well, Jean-Jacques, it's been a pleasure to have you on our show.
Thank you so much.
Thank you very much for inviting me.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for listening.
I hope you liked the show today.
If you enjoyed the podcast, please consider giving us five stars on Apple Podcasts.
Follow us on Spotify, support on Patreon or PayPal, and connect with us on social media
platforms.
See you next time.
Bye.